<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Diatelesma. The second part of the moderne history of the vvorld containing the last summers actions, in Languedock, Italy, Piemont, Montferrat, Lorrain, the Dukedome of Burgundy, the Franch country, and generally in France, Holland, the West-Indies, and marine occurrences; with some passages of Rome, and Turkey, brought downe to Novemb. 1637.</title>
            <title>Diatelesma. Part 4.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4293.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107082</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842785</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178347</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11899)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178347)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1599:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Diatelesma. The second part of the moderne history of the vvorld containing the last summers actions, in Languedock, Italy, Piemont, Montferrat, Lorrain, the Dukedome of Burgundy, the Franch country, and generally in France, Holland, the West-Indies, and marine occurrences; with some passages of Rome, and Turkey, brought downe to Novemb. 1637.</title>
                  <title>Diatelesma. Part 4.</title>
                  <author>N. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Harper, and are to be sold by Nathanael Butter, and Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Part 4 of five news tracts issued from 1636 to 1639, of which the last three are entitled "Diatelesma". "To the reader" of other parts signed: N.C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1616-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178347:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Diateleſma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond part of the Moderne Hiſtory of the VVorld, containing this laſt Summers actions, IN <hi>Languedock, Italy, Piemont, Montferrat, Lorrain,</hi> the Dukedome of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> the <hi>Franch</hi> County, and generally in <hi>France, Holland,</hi> the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and <hi>Marine</hi> occurrences; With ſome paſſages of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Turkey,</hi> brought downe to <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1637.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quicquid agunt homines noſtri eſt ferrago libelli.</hi>
               </p> 
               <bibl>Iuven.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative design</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Harper,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Nathaniel Butter,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Bourne.</hi> 1638.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:178347:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:178347:2"/>
            <head>A Table of Contents.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Erbellone</hi> encampeth before <hi>Laucate.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Situation of <hi>Laucate.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cerbellon</hi> gropeth the Governour,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And fayling of his end, prepares to batter the Fort.</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Caſtle of <hi>Roqueford</hi> taken by <hi>Cerbellon.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Garriſon re-enforced,</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Duke of <hi>Halewin</hi> prepares to relieve it.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Brings up his armie opportunely,</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Calleth a Councell of Warre.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The reſolution of the Councell,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is put in practiſe.</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Spaniſh ſcouts repulſed.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The French Generall ſeekes to be informed of the Spaniſh Fortifications,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Fortifications diſcovered,</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Another Councell of Warre is called,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>It being concluded to aſſault the Enemie in five places.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Labourerers are ſent to open the way for the horſe,</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And the French armie is divided into five bonds.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A reſerve ſet apart.</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The battels joyne.</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The fight doubtfull; the French horſe come up, and get the victorie.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Spaniards flye,</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The French ſeize on the ſpoyle.</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178347:3"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Spaniards loſſe.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The King gives thankes to God, and rewards to his ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Duke of <hi>Rohans</hi> march out of the <hi>Veltoline.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>D. <hi>Bernhard</hi> goeth into the field,</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Takes in the Caſtle of <hi>Romagne,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Which yeelds upon diſcretion.</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Some Peaſants, to ſecure their gold, loſe both money and lives.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Champlite</hi> ſurrendred to D. <hi>Bernh.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mercy</hi> with ſeventeeene Regiments, oppoſeth the D. paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage over <hi>Soan.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Duke <hi>Bernh.</hi> encounters him,</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And gets the victorie.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Giz</hi> yeelded upon diſcretion.</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Commander in Saint <hi>Loup</hi> hanged up.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The iſſue, and effect of the battell.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mercye</hi> againe defeated by the <hi>Rhinegrave.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mountbeliard</hi> blocked up by <hi>Putler,</hi> is freed by <hi>Schave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litzky.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Altkirk,</hi> taken, pillaged and burnt by <hi>Schavelitzky.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Montbeliard</hi> re-victualled by D. <hi>Bernhard.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Six Companies of <hi>Lorrain</hi> horſmen defeated by D. <hi>Bern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Boyſeys</hi> Regiment defeated, and himſelfe ſlain.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mommartin</hi> and <hi>Veſon</hi> taken in, the Duke marcheth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Rhine.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Many of the <hi>Lorrainers</hi> ſubmit to the French King volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Le Pont de Horde,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Beſieged,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And taken by the Count of <hi>Medovie,</hi> Governour of <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliard.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Governour hanged.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The death of <hi>Ponico,</hi> D. <hi>Bernhards</hi> boſome friend.</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178347:3"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A ſtrange tempeſt at <hi>Tours.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Buffara</hi> a Weaver, naiſeth a commotion in <hi>Perigot.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>By an ill woven ſpeech to the Peaſants,</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The people aſſenting, take up Armes;</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are beaten in the field by the Duke <hi>de Valette.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Their Captaine broke upon the wheele.</cell>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A black-Smith raiſeth a new commotion in <hi>Querey,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Taketh <hi>Fons,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is re-enforced by three thouſand freſh men,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Summons <hi>Pigear.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is deluded by the Citizens,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Taken, and delivered to the hands of Iuſtice.</cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Marqueſſe of <hi>Conſtans</hi> raiſed by the Duke of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueville.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Caſtle of <hi>Courlaon</hi> beſieged by the D.</cell>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Surrendred upon compoſition.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The towne of <hi>Lyon de Saulnier</hi> beſieged by the <hi>French.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>34.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Caſtle holds out.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Two other Caſtles taken by the Duke <hi>Longueville.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Montaigne</hi> taken by the Count <hi>De Guebriant.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Caſtle of <hi>Lyon de Saulniere</hi> ſurrendred upon compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Divers Forts and Caſtles taken by the D. <hi>de Longue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Caſtle of <hi>Sovigny</hi> ayred before the <hi>French</hi> enter.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> by ſuffering the <hi>Camptois</hi> to take their Crop, relieves his Army.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Orgelet</hi> yielded to the <hi>French,</hi> with other Forts.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Count of <hi>Soyſſons</hi> gives evidence of his loyaltie to the King.</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sundry Caſtles taken by <hi>Guebriant</hi> in the <hi>French Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>S. <hi>Lawrence la Roche,</hi> the Towne ſurprized by the <hi>French,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178347:4"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Burned by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> which ſlie into the Caſtle,</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Where they are beſieged, and forced to yield.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Bleteran</hi> in danger of a ſiege.</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Burgeſſes prepare to flie.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Guebriant</hi> way-layes them, and they not comming abroad, addreſſeth a Stratagem to ſurprize the Garriſon.</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>That fayling, he takes in <hi>Ioſſeau</hi> a Caſtle,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And the Fort <hi>de Loges,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Addreſſeth a new ſtratagem for the Garriſon of <hi>Blete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And ſurprized a part of the Preſidiaries.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Bleterans</hi> beſieged,</cell>
                     <cell>46</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And deſcribed.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Caſtle of <hi>Fontenay</hi> ſurrendred.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Towne of <hi>Bleterans</hi> taken.</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The beſieged flie to the Caſtle, where they capitulate, and ſurrender.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Troubles amongſt the <hi>Griſons</hi> after <hi>Rohans</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</cell>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leganez</hi> Governour of <hi>Millain</hi> goeth into the field.</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army is divided into three parts.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Gildas</hi> ſent towards <hi>Niſſe le Pagly.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Summoneth the Citie.</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Which by the treachery and ſeditious practice of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants,</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was ſurrendred,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>In deſpight of the Governour, and Garriſon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Agliano</hi> beſieged by the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Commander endureth divers aſſaults.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Slaughters upon the Aſſailants.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Agliano</hi> taken by the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Leganez</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campe neere each other.</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Màrqueſſe his Horſes quartered without his Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, are expoſed to damage,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178347:4"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Prince of <hi>Modena</hi> ſent into <hi>Langues,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Plundereth the Territorie,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Taketh in the Fort <hi>Santa Iulia,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Where he encampeth, and is raiſed by <hi>Senantes,</hi> a Colonell of the Duke of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Fort Royall built by <hi>Leganez</hi> at <hi>Rocca.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leganez</hi> diſcampeth.</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The <hi>French</hi> Army joynes with the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who ſends a part thereof againſt the Prince of <hi>Modena.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cairo</hi> beſieged by <hi>Verrue.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leganez</hi> to divert him, invades <hi>Veecelloia.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But his project takes not.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Battell betwixt the Marqueſſe <hi>Ville,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Forces neere <hi>Ceſia,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Begun by a light Skirmiſh,</cell>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Comes to a pitcht Battell, which a while continued doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet in the end the <hi>French</hi> get the victory.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>La Rocca</hi> beſieged by the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Piemontains.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A notable Exploit done by <hi>Dallot</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leganez</hi> ſendeth <hi>Don Martino</hi> to relieve <hi>la Rocca.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Vantguard ſurprized.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Leganez</hi> bringeth his whole Armie againſt the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Piemontains.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Battell without victorie.</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The ſiege of <hi>la Rocca</hi> raiſed.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The victory gotten by the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> at <hi>Monbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The death of the Duke of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>66</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The King of <hi>France</hi> cauſeth the Maſter of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To proclaime an Office for his ſoule.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Proclamation concerning the Dukes titles, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>67</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The manner of the ſervice with all Ceremonies.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178347:5"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The firſt dayes ſervice.</cell>
                     <cell>68</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Office for the ſecond day.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>With all the particular ceremonies.</cell>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Two Capuchins murdered by a Iew at <hi>Carriew.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The murder diſcovered.</cell>
                     <cell>73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Iewes condemned and executed.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Popes ſickneſſe and recovery.</cell>
                     <cell>74</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The death of the Dukes of <hi>Mirandula,</hi> and <hi>Mantua.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The States purpoſe to warre</cell>
                     <cell>76</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Breda</hi> beſieged.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The deſcription of the Towne.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The condition under ſeverall Princes.</cell>
                     <cell>77</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Avantguard under <hi>Henry Caſſimire,</hi> blocks it up.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Works begun.</cell>
                     <cell>78</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Cardinall <hi>Infante</hi> ſeeks to releeve it.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iohn de Naſſau</hi> ſent to deſcry the Princes posture.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Obſerving the Prince on his ſquadron, he departeth.</cell>
                     <cell>79</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Henry Caſſimire</hi> like to be ſurprized.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Garriſon ſally out upon the Campe.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Princes order to keepe the Garriſon in.</cell>
                     <cell>80</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Venlo</hi> taken by the Cardinall.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Rouremond</hi> ſurrendred upon compoſition.</cell>
                     <cell>81</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Articles of <hi>Breda.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>83</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> deſigne upon the rode of S. <hi>Tropez</hi> failing.</cell>
                     <cell>89</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet ſurpriſeth 10 <hi>Holland</hi> Ships bound for <hi>Genoa.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>91</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The <hi>Genoveſſes</hi> ſeeke to have them reſtored but prevaile not,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The arrivall of Count <hi>Maurice</hi> at <hi>Pharnam-Boucq.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>92</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>His Victory at <hi>Porto Calvo.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Gallies of <hi>Biſera</hi> pillaged the Sea-townes in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>95</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>izeroy of <hi>Naples</hi> provideth to ſerve them.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Coriale</hi> pillaged by the pirates of <hi>Alger.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>96</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Bendetty in the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> executed.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:178347:5"/>
            <head>Diateleſma.</head>
            <head type="sub">The ſecond Part of theſe Summers Actions 1637 brought down, and publiſhed as it was promiſed.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Victory atchieved by the</hi> French <hi>in</hi> Languedock. CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
                  <hi>Private man is happy in a medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity of Fortune, if he can content himſelfe with having what is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and ſufficient. A Prince by ſeeking to enlarge his Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, not ſeldome draineth his Exchequer, always increaſeth his cares, often his owne, and his peoples ſorrows.</hi> The Catholike King might ſeeme to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:178347:6"/> thrive the yeer paſt by his invaſion of <hi>Picardie,</hi> yet now ſhould it come to an <hi>Audit,</hi> his loſſes in <hi>France</hi> would (it ſeems<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſurmount his gain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, the Count <hi>Cerbellon</hi> encamped before <hi>Laucate,</hi> with an army (as the <hi>French</hi> affirme) of 16000 <note place="margin">Cerbellon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Laucate.</hi>
                  </note> foot, and 1800 horſe, an artillery of 70 peeces of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, a great number of wagons loaden with amuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, armes, and other neceſſary inſtruments, (all which had been in preparing the ſpace of two years) with a purpoſe to ſurpriz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome places of ſtrength in <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themſelves having ſeriouſly given it out, that the King in perſon was to command that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
               <p>The town is ſited in the ſouth of <hi>Languedock,</hi> called by <hi>Caeſar Gallia Narbonenſis,</hi> in a <hi>Peninſula,</hi> about 15 <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles in circumference of a triangular forme, bounded with rocks on the one ſide, a ſalt Lake called <hi>Salſes</hi> by the <hi>French</hi> on the ſecond, and the <hi>Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean</hi> Sea on the third, where there is a good Road for Gallies, and Ships of a reaſonable burden. The ſituation <note place="margin">The ſituation of <hi>Laucate.</hi>
                  </note> of the place, they adjudging that it would much advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage their incurſions into <hi>Languedock,</hi> cauſed <hi>Cerbel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> to bring his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> troops before the Fort, who firſt ſounded the Governour, the Lord <hi>de Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry,</hi> offering him in hand (as is written by ſome) 50000 Crownes, and promiſing him a yeerly penſion of 6000 to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray it, and in fine, finding his loyalty to the Chriſtian King his Maſter, his conſtancy being revived by memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the glorious death of his father, formerly Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cerbellon</hi> gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> of the ſame place, who being taken by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> preferred the conſervation of the Fort for the King his Maſters ſervice, before his own life, proceeded from treaty to violence, to try if the walls could abide the thunder of his Ordnance, and remayne as firme as the Governours heart, which hee had found many a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:178347:6"/> double Piſtolet proofe.</p>
               <p>Like a wiſe Commander, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided <note place="margin">And failing of his end pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares to batter the Fort.</note> firſt for his own ſecurity, before hee attempted any offenſive way againſt his Enemy: ten days he ſpent in entrenching himſelf upon a lane of fifteene perches long, (the place being no way elſe acceſſible, by reaſon of the ſalt Lake on the one ſide, and a ſteep Rock-plum-down, on the other ſide) where becauſe there was little ſtore of earth, he covered his trenches with a wall of ſtone and clay, raiſed eight foot, where the ground was higheſt, and fourteen or fifteen, where it was lower, with a Ditch before it, and a Mount be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind it, for the more convenient lodging of his Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetiers. Within his trenches he raiſed two Forts, one called after his own name <hi>Cerbellon,</hi> of four baſtions; another in a place called <hi>Franquie,</hi> to which the leſſer ſhipping and Gallies might arrive; beſides hee made many redoubts upon which he planted all his Canons, except 14 peeces, bearing bullets of 40 pounds weight, which he drew neerer the Fort, and divided into three batteries, the firſt at <hi>Gran</hi> of ſix peeces, the ſecond of four Canons right againſt the only ſpring of ſweet wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the <hi>Peninſula,</hi> many of his ſouldiers (being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled thither to relieve their neceſſities) loſt their lives in time of the ſiege, and a third of the ſame number of Guns, with the ſecond, raiſed neere the Bridge, which is layed over the narrower chanell, by which the ſalt Lake emptieth it ſelf into the <hi>Mediterranean.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His batteries began with his entrenching, but they were like the gentle diſtillations of ſome few drops of rain before a violent ſtorm, or the noyſe of the gliding, purling rivolets at the Spring-head, compared to the roaring falls of <hi>Nilus,</hi> in reſpect of what enſued after. <note place="margin">The Caſtle of <hi>Roqueford,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by <hi>Cerbel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi>
                  </note> His works being perfected, he firſt ſeiſed of the Caſtle of <hi>Roquefort,</hi> which hee garriſoned and fortified, to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178347:7"/> command that paſſage, and impeach the <hi>French</hi> forces, which might be brought by the way of <hi>Narbonne</hi> and <hi>Defferecavall,</hi> and next of the town of <hi>La Palme,</hi> and ſo blockt up the way from <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> and then played from all his batteries upon the beſieged Citadell inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly (the beſieged in the ſpace of 30 days, which the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> forces lay before the place, having taken pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe notice (upon an exact account) of 17000 Canon ſhot) in the mean time, making the beſt uſe he could of his Morteren and Grenadoes, which did the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants farre more harme then his Ordnance. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour had ſet up his reſt, reſolved to die, before hee would ſurrender a piece of ſuch importance to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the Kings enemies, and with the aſſiſtance of 300 men, (the number of his ſouldiers being increaſed to <note place="margin">The Garriſon re-enforced.</note> that height, by the acceſſe of two Companies, which were ſent unto him by the Duke of <hi>Halewin,</hi> Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Governour of that Province) maintained the place bravely, till the ſiege was raiſed, and then affirmed, that he ſhould have been able to have holden out three weeks longer, if the ſuccours had not come in, as they did, ſo maturely. Hee hid not, but ſecured himſelfe, by the ſtrength of the Fort, from the aſſailants vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But there is no cauſe of confidence in bulwarks and walls of ſtone, Famine will ſcale them in the end, though the Enemies Ordnance cannot bore them;</hi> the Duke of <hi>Hale-win</hi> held this poſition for an Aphoriſme, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed all care, ſummoned up his thoughts, uſed all art to relieve him opportunely, called a Councell of the <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Halewin</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it.</note> Biſhops and Nobility, and having adviſed with them, what was to be done, applyed the meanes which were moſt probable to cure that ulcer which began to gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grenate and ſpread it ſelfe in that Province. Hee mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered up the Regiments of <hi>Vitry, S. Aunez S. Andrew,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:178347:7"/> 
                  <hi>Caſtelan,</hi> and <hi>Murviel;</hi> and train bands of <hi>Montpellier, Narbonne, Beziers, Niſmes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zez, Carcaſſone, Lodeſve, Sevennes, Ganges, Mirepois, Ionquieres, Caſtre, Viellette</hi> and <hi>Valat,</hi> which ſerved as his Infantry. The <hi>Cavallary</hi> was compoſed of the Gentry of <hi>Languedock,</hi> his own company of men at Armes, and his life guard, which divided by him into eleven Squadrons, under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of ſo many ſeverall, valiant, and expert Leaders, at <hi>Narbonne, Sept</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, the time and place of the Generall Randevouz, marched the day following to <hi>Sigean,</hi> where they lay enquartered that night, and the night following, attending till ſuch ſtore of amunition and victuals were brought in, as were thought neceſſary for that expedition.</p>
               <p>It was then upon the nick when the <hi>French</hi> Duke came in with his Army to ſuccour the beſieged, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gunners had made a ſufficient breach in the wall, to try the courage and manhood of the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants by aſſault. The Duke of <hi>Cardonne</hi> Viceroy of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talognia's</hi> ſonne was come to the Campe, and had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enforced <note place="margin">Brings up his Army oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely.</note> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army, with a new accrewt of 1000 men: the Count <hi>de Serbellon,</hi> began to be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the prize, rode upon his Male about the Camp, to give directions, promiſed the young <hi>Don</hi> to ſhew him a freſh battery, the next day oppoſite to the place, upon which he had before played with his Canon, and both by geſture and poſture, word, and work, expreſſed a certain aſſurance of a ſpeedy and notable victory. But let not him, that is putting on his arms, brag as if he was putting them off. The chance of warre, is of all other moſt uncertain, and here if any where, we may averre:</p>
               <q>Neſcis quid ſerus vehat vesper.</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diſcretion looks about, before it undertakes an adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Halwein</hi> for all this apparance of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178347:8"/> imminent perill to the beſieged, went not on to ſuccour <note place="margin">Calleth a Counſell of Warre.</note> them without forecaſting what might be the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of his adventure. Hee would not involve his Friends in moſt certain difficulties of a greater impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to avoid a leſſer danger of more uncertainty. The beſieged brought to extremity, might capitulate, and come off with life and honour; the worſt was, but the loſſe of the place, which being in the Kings Country, was in all likelihood to be regained, though not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expence, the loſſe of an Army, and ſuch an Army as was drawn out of the moſt ſelected men of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, was of more importance, and though he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to try the utmoſt for his Friends relief, yet hee would not attempt it without good <hi>Adviſoes.</hi> Two Councels of Warre, beſides that at <hi>Narbonne,</hi> were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the one in the commencement, the other in the proſe quution of his action. The one at <hi>Sigean, Sept.</hi> 14/24, where he lay encamped, the other in the plain of <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> foure dayes after.</p>
               <p>The concluſion of the firſt conſultation was that <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencour,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Councell.</note> the Field-mar ſhall with his Avant-guard of the Army, ſhould go to take up his quartier, at the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Deferrecavall,</hi> and ſurprize the Caſtle of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quefort,</hi> whileſt the reſt of the Army might march up to him: The taske was an hard and difficult one, the paſſage was narrow, there could march no more then two abreſt, yet his willing induſtry over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came that difficulty, and with a word, a bare ſummons took in the Fort, the Commander according, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to depart with no other Armes then his ſword, and his ſouldiers with ſtaves in their hands. The <hi>French</hi> Generall followed with the main body of his Army, giving a teſtimony of impatience, to ſee the Kings Enemies ſo farre advanced in his Majeſties ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories: and the ſame day about one in the afternoon,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:178347:8"/> ſet his Army in battalia in the ſight of his adverſaries. This his apparition ſomewhat altered the courſe of the <note place="margin">Is put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Counts deſignes. He was not ſo abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of his power, as that hab-nab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he would deale with the <hi>French</hi> Duke in open field: the trenches in which he was hedged, were as ſtrong as the Caſtle, and there he meant to keep, unleſſe ſome advantage might invice him abroad. He took it in foule ſcorn to be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braved, yet would not adventure forth of his fortiſica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon doubtfull, much leſſe upon deſperate condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <note place="margin">The Spaniſh ſcowts repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> A glimpſe he had of the <hi>French</hi> forces, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew their number, nor their order perfectly. To be better informed of each particular circumſtance, 400 horſe were ſent out to deſery the <hi>French</hi> Army. <hi>Halewin</hi> ſoon perceived what was ſntended, and to detain him in his ignorance of the particulars, ſent out five ſelected companies, under the direction of a man experimentally proved both wiſe and valiant, the Lord <hi>de Boiſſat,</hi> to beat theſe diſcoverers back, which charge (fortune waiting upon his valour) he performed ſo happily, that he forced them to retreat, one part into their trenches, and another by the Lake <hi>de Salſes,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the way of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe actions were but the <hi>Proſcoenia</hi> of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>French</hi> Generall ſeeks to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications.</note> 
                  <hi>Tragoedie:</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Generall having thus defeated the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Count of his intelligence, endeavoured to informe himſelfe of his adverſaries fortifications. The day light might beſt inſtruct him, but would moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger him, the enemy ſtood all the next day in battalia behind his trenches, and waited for ſo advantagious an occaſion. The night though it could afford him but a confuſed notice, would more ſecure him, and that he made choyce of being content to ſatisfie his underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which before knew the advantages of the ground, with ſuch a generall diſcovery of his manner of encam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:178347:9"/> He knew before, that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> lay intrenched <note place="margin">The Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> amongſt rocks, almoſt unpaſſeable, eſpecially for his Cavallary, onely he deſired to ſee if there was any way left, by which he might reach them in their fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, although it muſt be done with much difficulty. The night preſented him with a paſſage on the right hand of the new Fort called <hi>Serbellon,</hi> but ſo obſcurely, that he durſt not adventure, till the day diſcovering the Landskip of the place more plainly, confirmed him, that he might probably leade on his Army that way, not without any, but the leaſt danger. Vpon this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, he cauſed the Commanders of the Army, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to meet in counſell, gave them a particular relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what he had ſeene, wiſhed them to prepare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 6 in the evening to execute, what he had deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for aſſaulting the enemy, and being ſeconded by <note place="margin">Another Counſell of warre is called,</note> 
                  <hi>Mayola,</hi> Lieutenant of the Guard, to the Cardinall Duke <hi>Richelieu,</hi> who was come that day to the Camp, with inſtructions from the Chriſtian King, his ſpeech was crowned with applauſe, by the generall votes of the officers, with an expreſſion of as much forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to performe, as the Generall propounded the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize.</p>
               <p>The houre drew on, and then after inſtructions to Arme, the Duke made a ſhort oration to his ſouldiers to encourage them to fight for the King, the Country, their wives, childrens, and their owne liberty, warned to be ready upon the ſound of the trumpets, ſelected <note place="margin">It being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in 5 places.</note> five times 80 men out of five regiments, to goe on as the Perdues of the Army, which he had divided into ſo many ſeverall parts, to aſſault the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> trenches, in ſo many ſeverall places, ordered them to march with their ſwords by their ſides, a Pike in one hand, and a Bavin in the other, for aſſiſtance of the labourers, whom he had appointed to open the trenches, and theſe being
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:178347:9"/> ſupported by <hi>Mayola</hi> and <hi>Heriſſon,</hi> a Captaine of the regiment of the Iſles, (yet ſcarſe recovered of the wounds which he received at <hi>Margarita</hi> and <hi>Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta)</hi> which offered themſelves to that ſervice, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their directions, performed their work ſo well, <note place="margin">Labourers are ſent to open the way for the horſe.</note> that in the ſpace of halfe an houre, the Perdues were earthed, and he Pioners had cut a way for the more eaſie bringing up of the <hi>French</hi> Cavallary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mayola,</hi> who by his preſence had encouraged the workmen, would alſo be the firſt relator of this ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, poſted backe to the Duke, told him what was done, and the Duke who longed after ſuch tidings, Went on immediately in the head of his Army, not ſtaying to give them a charge by word of mouth, with an <hi>Ite,</hi> goe you, like a faint-hearted Commander, but like a daring leader, declaring a <hi>Venite,</hi> come and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me, by his exemplary action. The places appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ſive ſeverall aſſaults, and the Commanders which were to manage them were theſe. The firſt place, was at the Bridge upon the mouth of the Salt-Lake, the charge whereof was committed to S. <hi>Aunez,</hi> and his regiment who was ſeconded by the ſouldiers of <hi>Narbonne, Beziers,</hi> and the Dioceſſe of <hi>Caſtres,</hi> a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Volunteers commanded by the Lord <hi>de Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone,</hi> a company of Muskettiers, horſemen of <hi>Tholouza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> under the Lord <hi>de Calvet,</hi> Treaſurer of <hi>France.</hi> The ſecond place was upon the ſea ſhore, at the Port <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">And the <hi>French</hi> Army is divided <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſive bonds.</note> and this was the charge of the regiment at <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedocke,</hi> which was backed by three companies of foot, brought into the Army, by the Lords of <hi>Ionquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, Cauviſſon,</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Mirepois,</hi> by a troope of 150 Gentlemen, friends and allies to the Marqueſſe <hi>d' Ambres,</hi> one of the Kings Lieutenants in <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock,</hi> and by a company of men at Armes, conſiſting of 50 Maſters. Betwixt theſe two places, on the right
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:178347:10"/> hand of the regiment of <hi>Languedock,</hi> a third place was committed to the truſt and valour of the Lord S. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew,</hi> and the military bonds of <hi>Niſmes</hi> and <hi>Caſtres,</hi> who was to be ſeconded by the Duke of <hi>Halewins</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men at Armes, which were to be backed with 60 voluntiers, and a troope of horſe under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Lord <hi>de Magalas.</hi> The fourth place depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the charge of <hi>Chaſtelan,</hi> who with his own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, and the Commons of <hi>Montpellier</hi> lead the Vant-guard, being ſeconded by the Count <hi>d' Aubyoux,</hi> who commanded the white Cornet of 100 Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the Marqueſſe of <hi>Mirepois,</hi> following him with 50 others of the ſame quality, and the Lord of <hi>Monſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus,</hi> who marched after the Marqueſſe with 60 men at Armes of his owne name, and kindred, was upon S. <hi>Andrewes</hi> right hand, and the laſt upon <hi>Caſtelans</hi> right hand, committed to the regiment of <hi>Vitrye;</hi> in the head whereof marched <hi>Clermont Vertilliard,</hi> the Field-mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, ſeconded by a body of Infantery, commanded by <hi>Murveill,</hi> and that by another, under the direction of the Lord <hi>de Vallat,</hi> all by the men of Armes belonging to the Duke <hi>d' Halewin,</hi> and two other companies, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der two other Commanders.</p>
               <p>All the Army was not to be engaged at once, a ſtrong <note place="margin">A reſerve ſet apart.</note> reſerve was ſet apart, to relieve their friends, if they ſhould hap to be neceſſitated, and that was ready to be ſupplyed by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> who by ſea, about ſuch time as both the hoaſts began to ſlack their hands, as weary of fighting, came in happily, with 4000 foot, and two ſquadrons of horſe, which he brought thither in ſuch veſſels, as the harbour was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, to ſuccour his confederates upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <p>In this order, upon a ſignall given by the diſcharge of 4 Cannons, the <hi>French</hi> Army marched up to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:178347:10"/> trenches, and began a doubtfull battell, both parties fighting couragiouſly, and victory hovering over both the Armies, without any remonſtrance, where ſhe would pitch. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the beginning ſeemed her favourites, the <hi>French</hi> Commanders and ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <note place="margin">The battels joyne.</note> appointed for the foure laſt places, were more diſheartened by a falſe report (that S. <hi>Aunez,</hi> who had the charge of the firſt aſſault, was beaten backe with loſſe of many of his men, himſelfe being deſperately wounded in the head with one Musket bullet, and in his body with many others) then the offenſive Armes of the enemy, though by them they received much dammage, being twice repulſed, not without ſome ſlaughter of men. But the Generall ſtill like himſelfe, by his word incouraged them not to faint, and leading on in perſon, charged upon the invadors ſo roundly, that he beat them backe againe to the ſquadrons, which were appointed to ſecond them. The <hi>French</hi> Cavallary was not yet come up, the foot onely had maintained this ambiguous fight, by the ſpace of two houres. In the end the prauncings of the horſe were heard, the Cavallary of both ſides met, and the violent ſhocks of their encounters gave the Infantry a time of breathing. <note place="margin">The fight doubtfull, the <hi>French</hi> horſe come up, and get the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> The Moone, whoſe light till then was ſhadowed by the interpoſition of a foggy-dark-thick-womb'd cloud, then began to peep out of her ſilver orbe, and ſtood as a ſpectatreſſe of the battell five houres together. So long ſhe lent her borrowed light to the directors of the battell, who by her aſſiſtance, ordered their ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons ſo well, that though they were often broke on both ſides, they were as often rallyed, no man being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to judge which ſide would goe off with conqueſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quis cladem illius noctis?</hi> the ſlaughter of men that night cannot be recorded without expreſſion of ſome compaſſion. <hi>Cynthia</hi> ſtood looking on till the rocky
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:178347:11"/> mountainous field, rough by nature, appeared more uneven by heapes of ſlaine men, and horſes which cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the earth, till thoſe hils which had bin ſo often cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of <hi>Neptune,</hi> who by her aſſiſtance, had oft rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his curly head above the ſhore, appeared an <hi>Acelda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> a field of blood: the <hi>French</hi> not without ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted loſſe having got the victory, (ſome of their chiefe Commanders having purchaſed it with their lives, (all the reſt with ſore wounds) and ſlaine far more <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> upon the place, and then ſhe hid her head under the earth, as unwilling to ſee that horrid confuſion, and ſo determined the battell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The adaequate object of wiſedome is, facienda, &amp; vitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da; things to be undertaken, and avoyded.</hi> Both the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had encountred with hazards and difficulties to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd <note place="margin">The <hi>Spaniards</hi> flye.</note> them. Now the darkneſſe of the night had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed the conqueſt from the victor, but could not make the loſer unſenſible of his dammage. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſaw his men utterly diſcomſited, few repairing to their colours, and to ſave the remainder, made a volley of ſhot about 2 in the morning, from the Fort of <hi>Serbel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> as if it had bin a ſignall to his ſcattered troops, to repair thither that they might be ready the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for a new fight, though it was (perhaps) but a trick to conceale his ſight, himſelfe and the remnant of his Army, preſently making towards <hi>Spaine</hi> by the way of <hi>Perpignan:</hi> the <hi>French</hi> ſtood in full battali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> till the morning, and at dawning of the day, marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> quarters, which they found abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the ſunne climing up the Eaſterne hill, by his ſplendor, diſcovered the way of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſtrewed with the Armes and baggage of the flying enemy, who had disburthened himſelfe of thoſe incumbrances to make his ſlight the ſpeedier. There needed no adviſe of what was to be done, the one part of the <hi>French</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:178347:11"/> Army, was ſent after the ſugitives, which overtooke the reare, and put the ſloweſt to the ſword, beſides great numbers which were ſlaine at the Well of freſh <note place="margin">The <hi>French</hi> ſeyze of the ſpoyle.</note> waters, during the time of the ſiege by the garriſon, and the ſlaughter of ſome of the reare-guard upon their ſlight, and thoſe as were ſlaine the ſame day upon the place of battell, 500 were taken priſoners, (as the <hi>French</hi> boaſt) for the moſt part Captaines, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med officers, and above 500 drowned in the ſea, and the Lake <hi>de Salſes.</hi> The other part went to riſle the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Campe, where they found a booty beyond common beliefe, and their owne expectation. <hi>Serbel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons,</hi> and all the officers tents ſtood whole, their Plate was unremoved, which with their beds and utenſils remained to the victors, who alſo ſeyſed of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals Mule, Coat, and ſtaffe of office, and ſent them to the King as a trophee of the victory. But this was not all the prey, which befell to the Conquerors. The night <note place="margin">The <hi>Spaniards</hi> loſſe.</note> which crowned them with this happineſſe, was the next which ſucceeded the Chriſtian Kings Birth-day, and as emulous of the glory thereof, preſented the <hi>French</hi> Army with further ſpoyles, (as the <hi>French</hi> write) all the Invadors Cannons, and Morterers, 500 Quintaux of powd r, 600 of Lead, (a quintane is 100 pound weight) 30 Wagons loaden with match, 7 or 8000 Bullets, 4000 Pikes, as many Axes, more Bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards, and fire-works, ſeven Wagons loaden with horſe-ſhooes, as many with iron nayles, 26 Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries cheſts, well ſtored with all manner of medicines, and victuals in abundance.</p>
               <p>Newes of this victory was brought to the King at <note place="margin">The K. gives thanks to God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to his ſouldiers.</note> 
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> who to expreſſe his thankfulneſſe to the Author, by a ſolemne ſong of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſgiving, <hi>Octob.</hi> 8. new ſtile, in the Church of <hi>Noſtre-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ame</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> the Q: the Cardinall, the Counſellours o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtate, and the officers of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178347:12"/> all the Courts of juſtice, with throngs of people atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at that ſolemne Service; and in requitall of the Inſtruments, honoured the Duke of <hi>Halewein</hi> with the Office of a Marſhall of <hi>France,</hi> and the inferiour Officers with rewards, tokens of his Royall love, the Canons of the <hi>Arſenall</hi> and Town-houſe, expreſſing the joy of his Majeſty in the Liberties of the people, and the Bone-fires, and continuall Acclamations of the people crying out <hi>Vive le Roy,</hi> teſtifying their affections, and ſincere love to his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:178347:12"/>
               <head>The Actions and Occurrences in <hi>Lorrain, Burgundie,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> County, <hi>Perigort,</hi> and <hi>Turena.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N aſpiring flame is not eaſily ſuppreſt, it often diffuſeth it ſelf about the matter caſt upon it, and recovereth the ayre, receiveth no hurt by the blow of a ſtaffe, but giving way to the harder body, without any ſenſible ſeparation of its parts, commeth together again. Such is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a true ſouldier, an affront by his Friends, an open deſertion of his Allies, cannot ſo much abate his ſpirit, as to make him lay down his armes, and give way to his adverſary, the ſtage of warre is large, and if one part thereof bee ſo incumbred that hee cannot doe his part there, he will act it upon another. The Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> by the practice of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> was hindred <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Rohans</hi> march out of the <hi>Veltoline.</hi>
                  </note> from promoting the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Kings affaires in the <hi>Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toline,</hi> marched thence with 800 horſe, and 4000 foot, men of braver inſides then outſides, tryed Lads, their weather-beaten garments teſtifying, that they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured ſome ſtorms of warre and weather, intending to joyne his Forces with the Kings Armies, either in the <hi>French-County,</hi> or <hi>Piemont,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hee ſhould receive order
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:178347:13"/> from his Majeſty, who was then preſcribing ſeverall Provinces to his ſeverall Generals.</p>
               <p>Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Weymar</hi> was appointed for the <hi>Rhine</hi> principally, but not with ſo ſtrict a Commiſſion, as not to encounter with the Kings Enemies elſ-where; ſome rubs were expected in his way, and it was in his election, whether hee would make any ſtay to remove them, the Chriſtian King thinking himſelfe ſufficiently honoured by the voluntary ſervice of ſo noble a Prince, ſo abſolute a Commander, not limiting him, which <note place="margin">D. <hi>Bernhard</hi> goeth into the field.</note> without chalking the way, knew both the manner, and time to further the Kings buſineſſe. His Majeſtie graced him with his perſonall preſence to <hi>Rhemes,</hi> the Metropolis of <hi>Campagnia,</hi> whence after a <hi>Dieu vous benie,</hi> God ſpeed you, and farewell, ordinary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, the Duke marched firſt to <hi>Langres,</hi> a towne in the midſt of <hi>Caeſars Lingones,</hi> now knowne by the name of the Province called <hi>Beſſigni,</hi> thence to <hi>Veſcay,</hi> and thence to <hi>Dampiere,</hi> the Generall Randevouz of his Army, where I finde him firſt preparing for action, <hi>Iune</hi> 3/1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The <hi>Almaine</hi> Forces which were to be condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to his Army under the Generall <hi>Major Schavelitzky</hi> did not then come in, nor was their ſtay prejudiciall to his deſignes, but <hi>Hallier</hi> his Lievtenant Generall met him with 4000 able horſe, and ſeven Regiments of foot, and attended with this retinue, he began to execute the Kings Commiſſion. The Garriſon of <hi>Gray,</hi> a town upon the Northweſt of the River of <hi>Sacue,</hi> right over againſt <hi>Auxounne,</hi> had lately got from the <hi>French</hi> the Caſtle of <hi>Romagne,</hi> a place of ſuch importance, that it being in the <note place="margin">Takes in the Caſtle of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magne.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Spaniards</hi> hands, did not only hinder all correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, betwixt the two great townes of <hi>Sangres</hi> and <hi>Diion,</hi> but did much annuſance to the whole adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning territory. It was well manned according to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:178347:13"/> proportion of its capacity, 120 ſouldiers, and thirty peaſants being layd into it, and better victualled, and this was the firſt place where hee imployed his forces. <hi>Tupadell</hi> his Generall Major was ſent before with the avantguard of his Army to ſurround it, the Duke imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that ſuch an apparition would be ſo terrible to the defendants, as to make them prepare for a capitulation. The iſſue was otherwiſe, the beſieged ſaw but a ſmall number of Enemies, and by the benefit of the Fort, thought themſelves ſtrong enough to grapple with them, they imagined that the Duke was confined to a day and place elſewhere, and would not ſtay to bring the body of his Army thither, and in this confidence ſcoffed at the Generall Major, as if he had undertaken a buſineſſe which he could not accompliſh: But <hi>ſe M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que qui cloque,</hi> they had no cauſe to ſcorne him, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantguard which preſented it ſelfe before the Fort, was but as a flaſh of lightning before a thunder-clap, two days after, the Duke himſelfe came downe in perſon <note place="margin">Which yiel upon diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> with the mayn body of his army, ſpent 100 great ſhot againſt the Caſtle, forced the Garriſon to yield upon diſcretion, made all the ſouldiers priſoners of warre, with their Captain <hi>Tournon</hi> Major of <hi>Gray</hi> and an <hi>Alfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eres,</hi> which commanded them. The peaſants were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed, and might have paſſed freely, had they not been diſcovered, to have concealed ſome Piſtolets which <note place="margin">Some peaſants to ſecure their gold, loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> both mony and lives.</note> were given to the ſouldiers as lawful pillage. Like thoſe <hi>Iews</hi> when <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was beſieged by <hi>Titus Veſpatian,</hi> they had ſhrined up ſome gold in their bowels, and that treaſure which ſhould have ſerved for their livelihood, was the cauſe of death to ſome of them (the ſouldiers apprehending them, and ripping up their bellies to find that Mine) and had been to all, if the Duke had not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed and reſtrained them, from proceeding ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:178347:14"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Champlete</hi> another Fort which much endamaged the Kings Country, ſtood next in his way, and this hee firſt ſummoned by a trumpet, <hi>Iune</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, and the day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by ſix Canons, which forced the Garriſon to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render and redeeme their baggage with a good and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Champlite</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred to D. <hi>Bernh.</hi>
                  </note> proportionable ranſome, and then the way being clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and theſe Caſtle committed to <hi>French</hi> preſidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, a part of our Army, marched directly towards the River of <hi>Soane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> with order to encampe about the towne of <hi>Briot,</hi> till the day following, which time he himſelfe came to them with the troops which atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is the ſouldiers glory to encounter with difficulties,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Weymar</hi> met with much oppoſition on his march, but never ſhunned it. The Colonel <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> in behalfe of <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with 13 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of horſe, and four of foot, though not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mercy</hi> with 17 Regiments op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the D. paſſage over <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>an.</hi>
                  </note> ones had planted himſelfe on the Eaſt ſide of the River, to hinder the <hi>Almain</hi> Duke and his <hi>French</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinew, from paſſing it. Tydings of the <hi>Lorrainers</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, were brought him, by the Vantcurriers of his Army, and he immediatly put his men into battalia, and marched directly towards the River point blanke againſt the place, a Village where the Enemies Army lay on the other ſide of the water. The ſight of the foe, ſtanding to diſpute his paſſage with arguments of ſteel, rayſed his bloud (not to an unadviſed anger, which ſhould make him neglect counſell, and without reſpect of danger, cauſe him to go on deſperatly) but to a well regulated emulation, and that expreſſed in action, his valiant heart being therby inflamed to make ſtrong and ſpeedy reſiſtance, againſt ſuch a daring Antagoniſt. At once, he both drew out a Squadron of horſe, and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to aſſay the paſſage, and beat off the <hi>Lorrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Dragoons,</hi> which lay intrenched beyond the flood:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:178347:14"/> and planting eight Canons upon an hill neere the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, levelled them againſt the <hi>Lorrainers</hi> Camp, which <note place="margin">Duke <hi>Bernh.</hi> encounters him,</note> making ſome ſlaughter of his men (the Cavallary ſent to that purpoſe, having happily paſſed the ſtream, twice diſcharging upon the <hi>Dragoons,</hi> being ſeconded by ſome Muſquetiers, which waded up to the arm-holes, to ſuccour their friends, cleered the paſſage, D. <hi>Charles</hi> his <hi>Dragoons</hi> perceiving almoſt 100 of their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions ſlain upon the place, amongſt which was their prime Commander, the Generall <hi>Major</hi> of that Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 100 wounded, and ſome taken priſoners, rety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to an hill for their better ſafety. But the change of ground could not ſecure them from the devouring ſword which purſued them; the whole body of the <hi>French Cavallary,</hi> without delay made over to their Companions, and Colonell <hi>Roſa</hi> Lievtenant of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Dukes life-guard, having found a more fordeable cut, brought that off Regiment of 800 men through the ſtream, to thoſe who had paſſed it before, which flankerd, or ſide-ways aſſaulted the <hi>Lorrainers</hi> forces, whileſt the <hi>French Cavallary</hi> them in fron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, neere the Village <hi>d' Arralogne.</hi> The battaile might have proved doubtfull if all Duke <hi>Charles</hi> his men had been ſonnes of one mother, if all had but the like courage to three <hi>Almayn</hi> Regiments which ſtood to it ſtoutly, &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the ſight valiantly alone by the ſpace of an hour, <note place="margin">And gets the victory.</note> after the reſt were ſled. But the tergiverſation of thoſe fugitives loſt the day, the <hi>Germans</hi> in the end too were compelled to give ground, by an orderly retreat from one Hill to another keeping their ranks unbroken, and themſelves from the Maſſacre, till being brought to a ſtraight paſſage, and roughly aſſaulted they disbanded in great confuſion, expoſing themſelves &amp; their friends to the ſword, or captivity, and their baggage for a prize
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178347:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:178347:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:178347:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:178347:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:178347:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:178347:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:178347:18"/> to their Enemy. The ſumme of all was thus. The <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainers,</hi> and <hi>Burgundians,</hi> the other part of D. <hi>Charles</hi> his Army, ſled to the neighbour Towns and Caſtles to ſave themſelves, but to the great damage of their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers; the town of <hi>Giz,</hi> whither the major part of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Giz</hi> yielded upon diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> them fled for ſhelter, was ſurrounded immediatly by the <hi>German</hi> Duke, who <hi>Iune</hi> 15/25, conſtrained both it and ſome other ſmall Caſtles, where hee found good ſtore of viands, to yield upon diſcretion; only the Fort of <note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in St. <hi>Loup</hi> hanged up.</note> Saint <hi>Loup</hi> held out two days longer to the paine of the Governour, who then yielding upon ſuch conditions, as the <hi>victor</hi> ſhould preſcribe him after the ſurrendry, (juſtice over-ruling mercy) was hanged according to the Law of Armes, for his ſawcineſſe, in preſuming to hold a place ſo weakly fortified againſt ſo puiſſant an army. All the three <hi>German</hi> Regiments, 50 perſons on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">The iſſue and effect of the battell.</note> excepted were ſlain, or brought into captivity, 500 dead corpſes of them being found upon the place, and 900 known to be taken priſoners, beſides ſuch as were kept ſecret by the ſouldiers for their ranſoms, and 3000 horſes gained by this victory. The priſoners of note were theſe. Firſt, the Count of <hi>Reux</hi> a Colonel, 2. two Lievienant Colonels, by name <hi>Siurry</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph Carr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3. ten Captains of horſe. 4. Nine Lievtenants. 5. Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Cornets. 6, 13. Quarter-maſters. 7. Thirty and ſeven Corporals. 8. Thirteene trumpeters, 9. Three Kettle-drums one Provoſt, 426 common ſouldiers, and 400 <hi>Dragoons;</hi> beſides women amongſt which was the wife to Baron <hi>de Langres,</hi> and a great number of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; the greateſt part of the ſouldiers freed themſelves from thraldome, by a voluntary tender of their ſervice to the Duke of <hi>Weymar,</hi> but 16 Enſignes gained by the victory, were ſent to the King as Monumentall tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phees of this atchievement, and are kept by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:178347:18"/>
               <p> This defeat was ſeconded by another, <hi>Mercye</hi> had rallyed up his broken Army &amp; with 2000 horſe applyed himſelfe to trouble <hi>Schavelitskyes</hi> paſſage, who was comming from the <hi>Rhinoward,</hi> with 3000 men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to attend the <hi>Alman</hi> Duke in this Expedition. Notice of the deſigne was brought to the General before <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mercy</hi> againe defeated by the <hi>Rhinegrave</hi>
                  </note> it was put into execution, commanded the <hi>Rhinegrave</hi> againſt him, who ſo behaved himſelf in the enterprize, that he ſlue 400 of them upon the place, put the reſt to ſlight, and purſued them two league to <hi>Veſou,</hi> one of the principall towns of the <hi>French-County.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilſt theſe things were acting about the <hi>Saone,</hi> ſome <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Montbeliard</hi> blocked up by <hi>Butler,</hi> is freed by <hi>Schavelitzky</hi>
                  </note> other of the forces appertaining to Duke <hi>Charles</hi> the Generall Butler and the <hi>French</hi> County appeared about <hi>Monbeliard</hi> a City almoſt at the head of <hi>Moſella</hi> in <hi>Lorrain,</hi> in all 4000 ſtrong, ſurprized, and ruinated the bridge &amp; Fort of <hi>Voiaucourt,</hi> and began to block up <hi>Montbelyard;</hi> but retreated againe upon the report of <hi>Schavalit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> march, whoſe very name grew formidable <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Altkirk,</hi> taken, pillaged and burnt by <hi>Scha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velitzky.</hi>
                  </note> by the ruines hee had made in the <hi>Sundgow,</hi> where he had taken <hi>Altkircke</hi> and the Caſtle, pillaged them, and burnt them to the ground, and now re-enforced by the <hi>Count de Grandcey,</hi> Commander of <hi>Montbeliard,</hi> who came to him, with 200 horſe, and 1000 foot, with their joynt Forces tooke in <hi>Porreutruy,</hi> in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Baſill,</hi> where they ſtayed ſome few days expecting dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from the Generall. <hi>Iune</hi> 25, <hi>July</hi> 5, they met his Highneſſe at <hi>Viller-ſexe,</hi> whither they brought up on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 2500 men, the roughneſſe of the way, and tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the journey making the reſt to lagge behinde upon the way. The Dukes forces, were now drawn all together, and though he haſted towards the <hi>Rhine,</hi> hee <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Montbeliard</hi> revictualled by D. <hi>Bernhard.</hi>
                  </note> would not leave the <hi>French County,</hi> without ſome am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler teſtimony of his ſincere reſolution to propagate
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:178347:19"/> the cauſe, which he had undertaken. Divers <hi>petit</hi> Forts and Caſtles in that only Province had ſubmitted to him, and out of their ſtore, he had revictualled <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliard,</hi> both with Corne and Cattell, and now for a farewell to the County, <hi>Iune</hi> 27, <hi>Iuly</hi> 6, he firſt viſited <hi>Beaulme,</hi> which ſurrendred the ſame day, and furniſhed the Army with proviſion for the belly, and amunition for warre; and then himſelfe and his Lievtenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Halliere,</hi> having drawne out 350 horſe, and 1200 footmen out of the army went to ſeeke out the Enemy about <hi>Bezauzon. Iuly</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, the Game ſprung of it ſelfe. <note place="margin">Six Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of <hi>Lorrain</hi> horſmen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated by D. <hi>Bernb.</hi>
                  </note> Six Companies of the <hi>Lorrainers</hi> light horſe, and life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard, appeared neer a Country Village therabouts, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted them, &amp; though for a time, they defended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves manfully, in the end vanquiſhed them, ſlue, and took the moſt part of them priſoners, and got all their Cornets and baggage. The Sunne had not reached the Meridian, when this Enterprize was accompliſhed, nor had the Duke of <hi>Weymar,</hi> yet attained to the Zenith of that days happineſſe, <hi>Ridet fatum quoi evexit ſubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ò, &amp; niſi miſereatur, rapit.</hi> Fortune deals with her creatures, as the yong Lion with the Dog, plays with it a while, and then kils it. <hi>Boyſey</hi> a man raiſed by Duke <hi>Charles</hi> to the dignity of a Colonell, as if Fate had ſent him to fill up the Creſcent of the <hi>German</hi> Dukes glory, with a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Boyſeys</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment defeated and himſelf ſlain.</note> full Regiment of 1200 men, came into the field, and was diſcovered not farre from <hi>Bezanzon,</hi> preparing to impeach the Duke in his way to the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and againſt him, ſome troops were ſent out, who defeated him, and made him pay for his ambition of glory, with his own life, and of above 100 of his men, and with the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of his ſonne, who had engaged himſelfe with his Father in that Expedition, and many other ordinary Souldiers.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:178347:19"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Mont-martin</hi> a Caſtle ſited advantageouſly, and the town of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſou</hi> ſtood ſtill in his way, and he meaning to have his paſſage cleere, would not leave them unviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Mont martin</hi> was ſummoned <hi>Iuly</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and yielded <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mommartin</hi> &amp; <hi>Veſou</hi> taken in the Duke mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth towards the <hi>Rhine.</hi>
                  </note> the next day upon diſcretion, <hi>Veſou</hi> was ſurrounded by the <hi>Dukes</hi> army the day after, and the inhabitants ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting their diſability to hold out a ſiege, ſurrendred upon compoſition. And here was the period of the Dukes ſtaye in the <hi>French County,</hi> after theſe atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hee marched towards the <hi>Rhine,</hi> deſirous to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>John de Werth,</hi> who was diſpatched by the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> to make head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him there. Duke <hi>Charles</hi> intending to joyne the remaynder of his army (abated already a third part and more) with the <hi>Bavarian</hi> followed him at a diſtance, and ſeeking to aſſiſt his Conſederate, loſt the love of his owne people, who ſeeing their late Prince more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of anothers, then his own territories, both the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and other inhabitants of the Dutchy at <hi>Nancy,</hi> and the <hi>Barrois</hi> came in by throngs, and voluntarily at <hi>Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Many of the <hi>Lorrainers</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the <hi>Fr.</hi> King volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily.</note> gave an oath of Allegeance to the Chriſtian King, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the hands of <hi>Oq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>incourt</hi> the Governour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Le Pont de Horde</hi> a place upon the River of <hi>Doux,</hi> in the Frontiers of the <hi>French County,</hi> was knowne to be garriſoned with ſuch men; as much troubled the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings Allyes, and ſubject in the adjacent territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yet he would not ſtay to encampe before it, nor ſend a trumpet to ſummon it, that charge was left to the <note place="margin">Le pont de Horde,</note> 
                  <hi>Count de Medavy,</hi> Governour of <hi>Montheliard,</hi> from whence it was but three leagues diſtant: The Governor according to his order. <hi>Iuly</hi> 7/17, committed the care of the deſigne to the Captain <hi>la Capelle,</hi> Serjeant Major of the Regiment <hi>de Perche,</hi> whom with 200 Muſquetiers, two Companies of light-horſe, and one peece of Canon <note place="margin">Beſieged.</note>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:178347:20"/> he ſent the ſame day, to take it in. The Captain according to the common courſe of warre, ſent firſt to ſummon it, and receiving not only a flat deniall, but a volley of ſhot, which wounded ſome of his ſouldiers, attending the Commanders refuſall, played upon it with his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, while <hi>Freſmey</hi> his Lievtenant had advanced up to them, and broke it down. <hi>A ſmall diſadvantage abates the edge of a Thraſonicall Braggart:</hi> He which before might have had any honourable conditions granted him, if hee would have deſired them, now began to beg for his <note place="margin">And taken by the Count of <hi>Medovy</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Montbeliard.</hi>
                  </note> life, and baggage, and that being denied by the Leaguer, which would not then, being ſo farre advanced, be tied to Covenants, and thus diſtreſſed, fearing to be ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the Fury, the iſſue wherof is fatall, hee ſubmitted without articling to the aſſiegeants mercy. <hi>The wheele of fortune turns in a moment, the ſpoake that erſt was higheſt, is preſently loweſt:</hi> The Sunne but two houres ſince, ſaw this Governour commanding like a <hi>petit</hi> Prince, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braving his Enemy, and returning words of defiance to the others admonition; and now ſees him a Captive, <note place="margin">The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hanged.</note> a ſlave marked for death, manacled, and led to executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Count of <hi>Medovy</hi> ſo adjudging it, that becauſe the Garriſon expected the Canon, and had done many out-rages with execrable cruelty in the vicinage, the Governour ſhould be hanged before the Caſtle gate, &amp; the Souldiers be made priſoners of Warre, if they would not ſerve under his Colours, which they did to recover their libertie, were tranſmitted to Duke <hi>Beru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hards</hi> Army, and diſperſed into ſeverall Regiments; that being ſevered they might not conſult to run away. The Caſtle was not great of building, but of ſome impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the prize therof ſecured the harveſt of that territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as far as to <hi>Neufchaſtell,</hi> and opened the way for the <hi>French</hi> Garriſons to make an inroad into the Mountain of <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:178347:20"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>It is but folly for man amongſt the multitudes of ſo many vanities, as attend mortality, to expect perpetuall felicity. Some moleſtations, are ſtill calling us to their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, and ſorrowes will intervene to ſeaſon our merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> The German Duke was not ſo much joyed in his atchievements, as dejected by the death of his boſome friend <hi>Ponica,</hi> a man whom above all other he had <note place="margin">The death of <hi>Ponica,</hi> D <hi>Bernhards</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome friend.</note> choſen out, to participate of his ſecrets, being both wiſe in counſell, and valiant in action. He was taken from him by a violent feaver in the midſt of <hi>July,</hi> and his embalmed body was reſerved in the Camp, till the Duke went to the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and then it was honourably interred at <hi>Baſill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor was the Chriſtian King without his Croſſe, though his forces abroad on the thriving hand, an inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection at home, by the <hi>Croquans</hi> in <hi>Pirigort,</hi> and the miſerable devaſtation of Towres, the Metropolis of <hi>Turena</hi> upon the <hi>Loire,</hi> by a ſtrange ſudden tempeſt, much diſturbed him.</p>
               <p>The dammage at <hi>Tours</hi> was unevitable, it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">A ſtrange tempeſt at <hi>Tours.</hi>
                  </note> not from the hoſtile Armes of an open enemy, nor the mutinies of rebels, but permiſſion of the divine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, againſt which, there is not a thought of conteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be entertained. The thing was full of admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, progreſſe and period. It was a great calme, with a little raine, when ſodainly, two dark clowds met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which belched out a winde intermingled with fire, and raiſed ſuch a tempeſt, as hath not been known in the memory of man. It was firſt perceived neere the wood S. <hi>Coſme,</hi> where it tore up the trees by the roots, and as in a moment, drive them to divers places, and thence extending it ſelfe to the City, overturned the moſt part of the houſes in the towne and ſuburbs, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly that of <hi>La Rich,</hi> which had not a chimney left ſtanding, nor a piece of the roofe to couer it, not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:178347:21"/> the Churches; S. <hi>Julians</hi> beſides the ſhattered windowes, having one of the ſteeples laid flat to the earth, and the other broke off in the middle: two of Saint <hi>Gratians</hi> Pyramids being blowne downe, with the windowes of S. <hi>Peter du Boyle,</hi> the Dormitory and chimneys of <hi>Marmonſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> a pannell of the wall in the <hi>Carmelites</hi> cloyſter, with ſo much more loſſe, as cannot well be repaired with one hundred thouſand <hi>French</hi> crownes. This was the progreſſe, yet the end was more wonderfull both in its time of duration, and the bounds of the tempeſt. It was ſuppoſed to be raiſed by ſome damned Sorcerer, who by the aſſiſtance of the Prince of the ayre had cauſed this outrage. The inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this deſolation was limited both to time, place, and perſons; the time laſted not above halfe a quarter of an houre: the <hi>Hericano,</hi> (ſo we may call it, though the true one was never ſeene in <hi>Europe)</hi> did not dilate it ſelfe beyond the City, and the Southerne banks of the <hi>Loyre,</hi> where it rent up ſome few trees, nor killed any, ſave only two men, which in a kinde of diffidence in the divine providence, were going to ſhelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Tower S. <hi>Hugon,</hi> their eyes having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held that ſtrong place caſt down by the violence of the ſtorme before their deaths, the ſupreame Majeſty reading a lecture to us all by their deſtruction, when they ſought for preſervation, that the aſſured meanes of temporall ſafety are not in our election; and that it is meere vanity to oppoſe his omnipotency.</p>
               <p>His Majeſties troubles by the mutinous rebels, were <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Buffara</hi> a Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver raiſeth a commotion in <hi>Perigot</hi>
                  </note> within his power to remedy. The heads of ſuch inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine commotions, are commonly baſe fellowes, neither fit for counſell in peace, nor command in warre; <hi>Jack Straw, Cade,</hi> and <hi>Wat Tyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne the ringleaders in ſuch inſurrections, and now <hi>Buffara,</hi> a Weaver in <hi>Perigot,</hi> overſhooting his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:178347:21"/> ſhuttle, would be a ſtickler in ſtate buſineſſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking ſome peaſants, men of deſperate fortunes, and more deſperate mindes, by an heape of words, ill cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, but plauſibly uttered, ſpake thus unto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is there any difference betwixt the King and us? we</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">By an ill wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſpeech to the Peaſants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>have the ſhape of men as well as he. His greatneſſe is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by us, whoſe ſhoulders muſt beare the heavy weight of all his impoſitions, if we will continue in ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to that too grievous a burden. There is ſcarſe one of us, but may know the ſweetneſſe of liberty; wee have bin apprentices, or hired ſervants, and then feeling the ſcourge of our maſters over us, we deſired to be our owne men, the expiration of ſome few yeares, delivered us from that ſervitude, and we rejoyced in that liberty: But what got we thereby? A ſlavery far above the former: while we lived with our Maſters, their purſes bore our char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, we neither cared for houſe-rent, nor pariſh duties, we did our worke, tooke our ordinary repaſts and reſt, not caring for the morrow. Now we are Maſters, but worſe ſlaues then formerly; we carke and labour, ſit up late, and riſe early, and hardly can maintaine our fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, yet muſt be taxed with ſuch burthens, as we cannot ſupport to maintaine a warre, undertaken for pleaſure, not profit to the Kingdome. The King hath provoked an enemy, with whom hee might have had peace, and Wee muſt ſuffer for it. We ſee the Frontiers of this Kingdome invaded, the</hi> Spaniard <hi>hath got ſome footing in</hi> Guyenne, Languedock, Province, <hi>and</hi> Picardie, <hi>it is to be thought he will goe on, and if we meane to ſave our ſelves, wee muſt not appeare in the Kings behalfe, and if wee meane to enjoy our ſtates, wee muſt take up Armes, and oppoſe the Kings officers, that purſue us with their exactions. I crave your reſolutions, and as many as will aſſent unto me, let them fling up their caps, and cry liberty.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:178347:22"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Each offence (like</hi> Horace <hi>his Crow in the Iayes fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The people aſſenting, take up Armes.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtruts in the colours of vertue)</hi> The rebell, which preferring his private intereſt before the common good, would alter the courſe of ſtate, in an <hi>Ariſtocratie</hi> uſhering in an <hi>Ataxie,</hi> in a Monarchie introducing an <hi>Anarchie,</hi> will have a plea of politie to varniſh his rebellion, and if he can but deliver it to the ignorant people in a fuſtian language, that many-headed beaſt doth oft receive it as Authenticall. The ſeduced people applauded his ſpeech, and as if <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itho</hi> had ſate upon his ſeditious tongue, aſſevered, that he ſpoke truth in all, tooke up Armes, choſe him for their chiefetaine, and in a deſperate madneſſe, following their more deſperate leader, ſearched the Merchants ware-houſes of that Province, ſlaughtered the Kings officers, proclaimed a day of Iubilie to as many as would take part with them, and by their progreſſe in the beginning, finding no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, increaſed their firſt number to 7000 men. <hi>Miſchiefe, though not well ſupported at the firſt; growes higher, like the luxuriant branches of a fruit-bearing tree: if a good Patriot, like a Gardner, put in his pruning hooke, the ſuckers are ſoone cut off, and the ſtocke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines entire.</hi> The Duke <hi>de Valette,</hi> ſonne of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <note place="margin">Are beaten in the field by the Duke <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Valette.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>d' Espernon,</hi> Lievtenant Generall of that Province, his old Sires yeers diſabling him from performing his office, ſupplyed his Fathers duty, ſummoned the traine bands of the Country, called together many volunteers, met them in open field, when they were in the height of glory, gave them battell, ſlew 1200 of them upon the place, and chaſed them to <hi>Bergery,</hi> a a City upon the <hi>Dordonne,</hi> a River which diſembo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it ſelfe into the <hi>Garonne,</hi> below <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> where they fortified themſelves, and ſtood in defiance of his Forces. The Duke omitted no meanes to reclaime or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:178347:22"/> ſubdue them: brought his Cannon into the field againſt them, but that did not ſo much as affright them, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them fairely, that their taxes ſhould be alleviated, if not totally taken off, but his oratory could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, yet at laſt with the old ſtate tricke of a pardon, <note place="margin">Their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain broke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wheele.</note> made them ſubmit, and deliver up their Captain into his hands, whom he commanded to be broke alive up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wheele, in the high way, as an exemplary pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of juſtice, and diſmiſſed the others in peace to their own habitations.</p>
               <p>A black Smith, a Farrier, born at <hi>Lavergne</hi> in <hi>Quir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">A blacke Smith raiſeth a new com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion in <hi>Quercy.</hi>
                  </note> at the ſame time made another inſurrection in that Province, and upon the like pretext, had drawn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 3000 men from <hi>Tegrac, Lavergne, Padicar,</hi> and other places of that territory, who gracing himſelfe by the name and title of Captaine <hi>Baſque,</hi> and attended with this goodly retinue, went firſt to <hi>Gramat,</hi> a wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led towne, within one league of <hi>Lavergne,</hi> and thence enforced the proprietor, the Count of <hi>Cabeces</hi> to flye, having ſlain five or ſixe of his domeſticke ſervants, whom he had ſent to reſtraine his inſolent diſorder. Proud of his ſucceſſe, he proceeded further, went to <hi>Fons,</hi> neere <hi>Figear,</hi> a ſmall walled towne, but not gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſoned, <note place="margin">Taketh <hi>Fons.</hi>
                  </note> commanded the inhabitants to open their gates and receive ſuch conditions as he would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them, which they durſt not refuſe, there being no Army in that peaceable, and by peace over ſecure Country to reſiſt him. His ſucceſſe in the firſt attempt, made him entertaine a conceit, that he was a good Commander, but the fortune of the laſt, raiſed him from an opinion of his owne worth, to a ſure confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ability, the bladder of his timpanons ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Is re-enforced by 3000 freſh men.</note> being blown up, by the breath of 3000 other vaine fellowes, which came in to his aſſiſtance. <hi>Buffara,</hi> in the adjoyning territory, had given him a preſident of vaine
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:178347:23"/> arrogancy, and he intended to out-doe him in his folly. His attendants took upon them the name of <hi>Croquans,</hi> as well as thoſe under <hi>Buffara,</hi> and to make them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble military men, that they might goe into the field with colours, he robbed the Churches of their Pennons, and Banners, imployed and uſed them as Enſignes: and that he might appeare another <hi>Salmoneus,</hi> armed with falſe thunder, he took a tree of proportionable bigneſſe, boared and ſhaped it like a piece of great Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, thinking thereby to be more formidable. <hi>Waſpes make combes, and Apes imitate men:</hi> and Smug would reſemble S. <hi>George</hi> on horſe back.</p>
               <p>In this equipage he preſented himſelfe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. before the City <hi>Figear:</hi> firſt, ſeyſing of the ſuburbs, which the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants had abandoned upon the report of his march <note place="margin">Summons <hi>Pigear.</hi>
                  </note> thitherwards, and then ſummoning the town to open the gates, and to admit him in, with the black guard which followed, his ragged regiment. The inhabitants ironically humbly petitioned him, to ſtay till morning, acknowledged his victorious Armes, but that they might not be proclaimed traitors to the Crowne, and forfeit their charter, they onely requeſted a ſhort time of deliberation. The Farrier yeelds, plants himſelf that <note place="margin">Is deluded by the Citizens.</note> night in the ſuburbs, expects the ſignall of his intramiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the next morning, when ſodainly he was ſaluted with haile-ſhot from the walles, order being taken that the Lord <hi>Camboulye</hi> then reſiding in the City, ſhould place himſelfe there, with the old men, and ſuch as could doe no other ſervice, to diſcharge the ſmall Guns againſt him, whileſt the Lord of <hi>Roquefort</hi> with ſuch a Cavallary as could be ſuddenly raiſed in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Baron of <hi>Marinall,</hi> with 500 armed Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, ſhould ſally out againſt him. The ſhot ſtartled him, and made the Peaſants give ground; but <hi>Roque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> and the Baron ſoon after falling upon the Rebels
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:178347:23"/> with all their might, beat them out of the firſt Barrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, drove them to the end of the ſuburbs, where while their leader was rally ing his diſordered band, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to renew the combat, the ſouldiers of the City gaue them ſuch arough charge, that the moſt of them being ſlaine, the reſt were compelled to flye for their lives to <hi>Fons,</hi> which they had ſurprized the day fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going, <note place="margin">Taken and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the hands of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</note> whither the Baron of <hi>Marinal</hi> purſued them, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing execution upon the Reare, and beſieging the reſt in the towne, which they had taken for their ſecurity. The rabble of Rebels no ſooner perceived themſelves thus ſtraitned, but they humbly begged licence to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn in peace to their own homes. They were natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Kings ſubjects, born in his dominions, and had ſworne to perſiſt in a faithfull obedience to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and the Baron therefore was unwilling to proceed in extremity againſt them, though they had given ſuch an euidence of diſloyalty, it was reputed miſpriſon, not malice which cauſed the common men to offend, and though it was in his power to puniſh them exemplari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he concluded it to be farre better to win their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions by an act of mercy, then to eloigne the hearts of their fellowes from him, by proceeding againſt them legally. Yet ſtill he kept at a politike diſtance from them, painted out the hainouſneſſe of the treſpaſſe in glaring, oylie colours, told them he could not anſwer it before his Majeſty, if he ſhould ſuffer them to eſcape unpuniſhed, and all to make them ſenſible of their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, which he did ſo effectually, that the poore ſoules perceiving what they had done, humbly begged par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, which he granted conditionally. Firſt, that they ſhould deliver into his hands, their Captain, Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the Enſignes with the colours. Secondly, that each man ſhould return to his own dwelling, and ſweere never more to meet with any intention to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:178347:24"/> the Kings ſervice: both which conditions were performed the ſame day, and the Captain, Lieutanant, and Enſignes, were delivered to the officers of civill juſtice, to be proceeded againſt as criminall melefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, guilty of high treaſon: the Baron of <hi>Marivall</hi> preparing for his journey to <hi>Paris,</hi> to informe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the particulars which had bin done.</p>
               <p>Thus the Kings forces were happily victorious over the Rebels, which had raiſed theſe inteſtine commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons within his own dominions; nor were his Armies which were ſent againſt the frontier Prouinces under the <hi>Spaniards</hi> command unfortunate, either when they undertooke the recovery of what the King had loſt, the yeare paſſed, or made an invaſion into the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories. The Comtois were freed of D. <hi>Bernhard,</hi> but not of all the Kings ſouldiers. The D. of <hi>Longueville,</hi> Lieutenant Generall to the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> had drawn together all the <hi>Frenches</hi> which had wintred in <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne, Lorraigne,</hi> and <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and expecting to be re-enforced by the old ſouldiers, which came out of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> under the Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> who by reaſon of the indiſpoſition of body, being forced to ſtay at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva,</hi> was tranſmitting his 500 horſe, and 4000 foot to <hi>Longneville,</hi> though yet attended onely with his owne men, marched directly againſt the <hi>French</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and began his work where Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> left, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advancing the Kings buſineſſe, and more perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his enemies. His firſt quarter was at <hi>Branges,</hi> whence I finde him marching, <hi>Iune</hi> 11/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. and encamping the ſame night neer <hi>Faix</hi> with his Army. Till then he found occaſion to make experiment of his mens cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, or his own forrunes. Here he found a ſmall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture <note place="margin">The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe nf <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flans</hi> raiſed by the Duke of <hi>Langueville<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </note> to try his proweſſe. An expert <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, the Marqueſſe of <hi>Conflans,</hi> was encamped neer him with three regiments, againſt him he diſpatched
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:178347:24"/> 
                  <hi>Guitry</hi> the Field-marſhall, with one part of his Army, who, undiſcovered till hee had reached his Enemy, charged him ſo ſuddenly and furiouſly that had not the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Commander bin very carefull to hold his forces in their military order, his Regiments had bin rowted, and yet his care could not enable him to maintain his trenches, rayſed he was, but not diſcomfited, receding in a well ordered retreat, ſome of his <hi>Cavallary</hi> being ſlain, he ſaved the remayn of his men two leagues, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one <hi>Cornetto,</hi> one <hi>Guidon,</hi> his plate, and all his bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, as a booty to <hi>Guitry,</hi> whoſe ſouldiers more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of that prize, then a glorious victory ſtayed to pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage his Campe, not purſuing him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>June</hi> 12/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1, the Duke incamped neer the Caſtle of <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laon,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Caſtle of <hi>Courlaon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the D.</note> which he rounded with his army the ſame day, but not without oppoſition of the Garriſon, which played upon him from the Caſtle, and wounded <hi>Gondreville,</hi> his Armour-bearer cloſe by him, and not far from him, <hi>Fevillan</hi> and <hi>Rembe</hi> two Captains of the Regiment <hi>d' Anguyen.</hi> The Vicount <hi>Arpajoux</hi> Field-marſhall, was imployed all night to plant a battery againſt the Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, whiles the labourers, and ſome ordinary ſouldiers were ſent to get bavins to fill up the two ditches about the Fort, both which did their parts ſo carefully, that by break of day, the great Ordnance began to thunder, the pioners had filled up the outward ditch with fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots, <note place="margin">Surrendred vpon compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and plained the way for their eaſier acceſſe to the other; the great Guns had made a reaſonable breach in the wall, and the ſouldiers, each man with a faggot in one hand, &amp; military inſtruments in the other, were haſting to fill up the inward ditch, and prepare for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, by eight the ſame morning, when ſuddenly a white flagge appearing upon the wall, a retreat was ſounded, the <hi>French</hi> Aſſailants made a ſtop, and the Garriſon condeſcended upon condition of life ſaved to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:178347:25"/> ſurrender the Citadell. Leſſe could not have bin deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, more perhaps might have bin granted, if it had bin requeſted: to this petition the Duke ſubſcribed willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; ſo without effuſion of bloud, got tile Fort, where he ſpent the next day to refreſh his Army, repaire the breaches, renew the Fortifications, accommodate the place with a Garriſon, and to diſpoſe of the amunition, and other commodities found there, for his beſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and ſubſiſtence of his Forces.</p>
               <p>A worſe Fate attended a neighbouring City <hi>Lion de Saulnier,</hi> then befell the Caſtle, it was a place late of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <note place="margin">The town of <hi>Lyon de Saul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier</hi> ſurprized by the <hi>French.</hi>
                  </note> in the County, the ſalt pans adjoyning yielding a good annuall revenew to the inhabitants, and they again adorning the place with goodly edifices, teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their wealthineſſe. Now it muſt both change its Lord, and loſe its ſplendor. <hi>Iune</hi> 14/24, the Duke went in perſon to ſurvey it, and the ſame day begirt it with all his power. The Garriſon defended it well, whiles it was theirs, and when they could not hold it, ruined it. The <hi>French</hi> got it by piecemeal, firſt, the cloyſter of the <hi>Capuchins,</hi> then the Suburbs of Saint <hi>Deſire,</hi> and the town afterwards; yet we cannot properly ſay they got it, though the <hi>Spaniard</hi> loſt it, unleſſe the <hi>Spaniards</hi> loſſe may be called their gain; the Garriſon as it gave ground, <note place="margin">The Caſtle holds out.</note> ſo the Aſſailants gave fire to the Cloyſter, Suburbs, and City, which put the beſiegers to a new trouble, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſave what they could from the devouring <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> while <hi>Rimcourt</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Commander incloſed himſelf in the Caſtle, the ſtrength of the City wel moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, well walled, and then of the more difficult acceſſe, becauſe the Dike was brim full of water; and hee had broken down the bridge, which led into the Caſtle, leaving the rubbiſh of the towne a prize to the aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants.</p>
               <p>Yet though the Duke could not then take that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:178347:25"/> two others the ſame day became ſubject to the <note place="margin">Two other Caſtles taken by the Duke <hi>Longueville.</hi>
                  </note> King by his and his Confederates meanes. <hi>Sancourt</hi> a Captain of one of his troops of horſe, took in the Fort of <hi>Chilly,</hi> and the <hi>Count de Guebriant,</hi> Lievtenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to the Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> who that very day came up with his Forces to the Army, by the way took in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame vicinage.</p>
               <p>Mutuall ſalutations were ſcarce paſſed, betwixt the Duke the Generall, and <hi>Guebriant</hi> the Field-marſhall, when the Towne and Caſtle of <hi>Montaigne</hi> ſited on an hill, in the view of <hi>Lion de Saulnier,</hi> preſented it ſelfe to the Counts eye. <hi>An active ſpirit apprehends each occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be doing:</hi> The Count though he could not but be weary of his late march, expreſſed a kind of impatience <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Montaigne</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Count <hi>de Gue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briant.</hi>
                  </note> in his looks, till he might come to action; acquainted the Duke with his purpoſe againſt <hi>Montagne,</hi> and the Duke as forward to give way to the deſigne, as the Field-marſhall was to undertake it, gave him licence to uſe his forcé there without tying him to conditions. The Count marched againſt it, and carryed the towne, though the Commander tracing the ſteps of <hi>Rimcourt,</hi> intended to fire it, and in the end the Caſtle upon Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, that the Peaſants which ſurmounted above the number of 100, who were in the Fort, ſhould yield upon diſcretion: and the ſouldiers with their armes, without baggage, ſhould have convoy to ſome place of the Catholike King, which being not ſpecified, were ſent to <hi>Perpignan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matters of danger, not despair, are the true objects of valour: Every vertue is tied to Rules; and bounded with limits not to be tranſgreſſed, the extremes alter all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if they be pitched upon: courage loſeth its merited honour, if wilfulneſſe and unguided petulancy over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear it: a well grounded reaſon, without prejudice to a</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:178347:26"/> 
                  <hi>mans honour, may juſtly countermand a raſh and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate reſolution.</hi> It had bin diſhonourable for <hi>Rime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court</hi> to yield upon the firſt ſummons, and to hold out, it was almoſt impoſſible. Nor could the aſſaylant en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force him, but by famine, nor his friends relieve him if it ſhould have come to that exigent. The place was pent up with numbers of ſouls within it, the ſtrait con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of a Caſtle ſcarce could containe his ſouldiers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting <note place="margin">The Caſtle of <hi>Lyon de Saul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere</hi> ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred upon compoſition.</note> to 600 in number, and the inhabitants which ſurmounted that account, the Peſt was hot amongſt them, and payed a greater tribute to the grave, then the Enemies ſword. <hi>Pharaohs</hi> leane Kine preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves daily before him, the people began to cry out for bread, a morſell would have contented them, which before fared delicately every day, and were not pleaſed without variety of dainty diſhes: Relieve them hee could not but by an hard purchaſe of their liberty, nor be eaſed of their clamours, but by abſenting himſelfe from them, and that could not be archieved without the aſſent of his Enemy, and therfore he rather reſolved to buy his quiet upon hard covenants, then endure that vexation, which otherwiſe muſt neceſſarily purſue him. Capitalate he would, and upon any termes ſurrender, and capitulate hee did, and ſurrendred upon a ſtrange Article, which though in the Generals it ſavoured of providence, was a plain evidence, that harder termes would have bin accepted, if they had bin required, <hi>viz.</hi> a convoy for the Garriſon to any of his Catholike Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties townes, which the Duke accepted, imbarqued them in ſo many Bottoms, as were required for their tranſportation, and carried them down the <hi>Saone</hi> into the County of <hi>Rouſillon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt wheele of an Autocineton, a ſelf-moving En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine being ſet a going the others muſt follow: It is ſo in</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:178347:26"/> 
                  <hi>warre, one prime place yielding, the appendants muſt come in too.</hi> The Caſtles of <hi>Crevecaur, Chilly,</hi> and <hi>Eſtoille</hi> in the <hi>French County,</hi> as if there had bin a contignation of their ſeverall buildings, ſunke with the mayne piece of that Fabrick, the Caſtle of <hi>Lyon de Saulnier</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">Divers Forts and Caſtles taken by the D. <hi>de Longue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville.</hi>
                  </note> enforcement rendred themſelves to the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> his Majeſties Lievtenant Generall, who poſſeſſed himſelf of them to the uſe of the Chriſtian King his Maſter. The Fort of <hi>Savigny</hi> in the Province of <hi>Breſſe,</hi> made ſome reſiſtance, and detained him ſome few days: The <hi>Spaniard</hi> had got it by his puiſſance the yeer before, and would not let it go without knocks; <hi>A private man is more tenacious of what he hath got by his own induſtry, then what deſcends unto him by inheritance: The Souldier, like the Merchant, will ſell dear when he pays dear.</hi> The others places deſcended to the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> by marriage, this was purchaſed with bloud, and nought but bloud could redeem it, 14 dayes the Garriſon held out, from the 2/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Iuly</hi> new ſtile, to the 16, and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter blows both given and taken, was conſtrained to yield, upon condition that the Garriſon conſiſting of 200 men ſhould be convayed to ſuch one of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Kings townes, as it ſhould pleaſe the <hi>French</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is no happineſſe to be poſſeſſed of much, if there be no uſe to be made thereof.</hi> The Caſtle of <hi>Savigne</hi> opened her gates to let the <hi>French</hi> in, but as yet they durſt not truſt themſelves within the walls therof, the <hi>Spandards</hi> were gone, but left a more dangerous foe behinde them: the ayre was infected with peſtilent exhalations threatning an unavoidable deſtruction, to as many as ſhould dare to draw breath there: To make it ſecurely habitable, the Dukes firſt care was to have it well ayred, and having purged it of the ſtench, ſilth and putrifaction, which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:178347:27"/> cauſed the contagion, about three weeks after, put in a <note place="margin">The Caſtle of <hi>Sovigny</hi> ayred before the <hi>French</hi> enter.</note> 
                  <hi>French</hi> Garriſon. The time which was ſpent thereabout was not conſumed vainly, order was taken by a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Ordinance for the ſuſtentation of his Army, which though it was imployed to the proper uſe of bearing armes againſt the Kings Enemies, was by that meanes provided for plentifully, by the peaſants of the <hi>French County,</hi> not of love, but fear, while the ſouldiers follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own profeſſion, handled not the Sicle to cut down the ripe Corne, but the ſword to cut off their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries: The <hi>French County</hi> was full of grain, the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt anſwered the ſeed-time, and the plowmans hopes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but they which ſowed it, durſt not mow it, leſt they ſhould both loſe their labours, and lifes in that adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. To ſecure the labouring Husbandman, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for his Campe at once, by a Proclamation hee au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed the <hi>Comtois</hi> to gather in the fruits of the earth of what ſort ſoever, with a condition, to bring in the <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Long,</hi> by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tois</hi> to take their crop, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves his army</note> third ſheafe, ſhock, or riſpell unto his Magazine. The covenant was received joyfully, and the peaſants with ſhew of alacrity, brought in the thirds of their Country commodities glad to have an aſſurance of two parts, which feared they ſhould loſe the totall.</p>
               <p>And yet the effects of this Decree, were not the mayn ſumme of the account, which the Duke could make of his time there. His forces came to action, and whilſt the Country people by ſupplying their wants, ſtrengthened their hands and hearts, they advanced the Kings deſignes. The Duke was informed by ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had made a little head, had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together betwixt <hi>Poligny,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Ruffe,</hi> and himſelfe in perſon attended with 1200 horſe, and 5800 Muſquetiers went from the Camp at <hi>Savigni</hi> three days before it was ſurrendred to give them battell.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:178347:27"/> His intent was to have cruſht the Cockatrice in the ſhell, to have abated that little body, which was in growing, before it came to perfection, but that project prevented by the providence of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Colonell <hi>Maillart,</hi> who commanded thoſe forces, and hearing of the Dukes march, retreated to a place of more ſecuritie, betwixt <hi>Salines</hi> and <hi>Bezanzon,</hi> he took occaſion by his own eye to informe himſelf of the States, and ſtrength of <hi>Bleterans, Poligni,</hi> and <hi>Arbois,</hi> the taking in of which places would prevent the Enemy of all meanes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing againſt the Kings towns in <hi>Breſſe,</hi> and <hi>Bagez,</hi> while the <hi>French</hi> armies were buſied elſewhere, and then returned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iuly,</hi> 5/15, he went again from his Quarter in the Camp, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orgelet</hi> yielde to the <hi>French</hi> with other Forts.</note> towards <hi>Cowleige,</hi> and thence again the next day to <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelet,</hi> to beſiege the Towne and Caſtle which defended it, where the Suburbs being maſtered by the Vicount <hi>d'Arpajoux</hi> his Lievtenant Generall, the beſieged fired the towne, and betook themſelves to the Caſtle, which they thought was ſtrong enough to ſecure them, and they able to hold, but were forced to yield the ſame day upon diſcretion. Many hands make light work, <hi>Savigni</hi> by this was reduced to extremities, and ſtood upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, only a part of the hoaſt was left before it, the reſt were commanded upon ſeverall adventures. The Baron of <hi>Cowpet,</hi> with the Regiment of <hi>Anguien,</hi> was ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Caſtles of <hi>Montonne, Pymorain,</hi> and <hi>latour-du-May,</hi> which he took ſucceſſively upon accord, and laſt againſt the Caſtle of <hi>Clervall,</hi> which he took by aſſault, put the preſidiaries to the ſword, and tooke three En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and two Cornets, which he ſent to the King by <hi>Ramboy Aide</hi> of the Campe to the Dukes army, as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numentall tokens of his atchievement.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty received ſome content in the happy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:178347:28"/> of his Forces againſt the profeſſed Enemies of that Crown, but more in the ſucceſſefull negotiation of <hi>Bautru</hi> a Counſellor of State, whom he had employed to feele the pulſe of his late diſcontented Couſin, who as a ſubject ought him all dutifull obedience, and by the obligation of Conſanguinitie, being his neereſt Kinſman of bloud, was tied unto him by nature, but upon a cauſeleſſe diſtaſte, in a Male-content was retired to <hi>Sedan,</hi> where <hi>Bautru</hi> being admitted to conference with him, diſcharged his office ſo effectually, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the Kings good affection towards him, hee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed <note place="margin">The Count of <hi>Soyſſons</hi> gives evidence of his loyalty to the King.</note> thoſe clouds of doubts, which had hovered o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his underſtanding, and made him entertain ſome jealous thoughts againſt his Majeſty, and after hee had got ſome evidence of his loyall heart, returned again to his Majeſty, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 3 new ſtile, with the welcome ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of his ſincere and unfained obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 6/16, was a day to be recorded in the <hi>French</hi> Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendars, and ſet downe in golden letters. <hi>Guebriant</hi> the Field-marſhall, being ſent out that day by the Duke of <hi>Longuevill,</hi> againſt the Caſtle of <hi>Bournay,</hi> which was kept by a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captaine, ten ſouldiers and 200 pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, after 58 vollies of Cannon-ſhot, forced it to yield upon diſcretion, and truſſed up three of the Souldiers, cauſing them ſo to ſuffer exemplarily, marched himſelfe againſt the Caſtles of <hi>Pibly, Ruargues,</hi> &amp; <hi>Preſilly,</hi> which he ſurprized, and ſent the life-guard of the Duke of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han</hi> with 400 Muſquetiers, to <hi>Beauregard</hi> and <hi>Binan,</hi> which they ſeized of, doing ſuch ſervice thereby to the King, that beſides the ground which they had gotten in the <hi>French County,</hi> which gave them good footing there, there being no place of ſtrength in their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies <note place="margin">Sundry Caſtles taken by <hi>Gue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briant</hi> in the <hi>Brench County.</hi>
                  </note> hand, from Saint <hi>Claude</hi> to <hi>Bleterans,</hi> ſave only S. <hi>Lawrance de la Roche,</hi> nor no place in the Frontier which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:178347:28"/> might ſerve as a convenient Randevouz for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armies, which were then on forming, but <hi>Salines</hi> in the two only Caſtles of <hi>Elymorain,</hi> and <hi>Beauregard,</hi> a booty was found worth in eſtimation above 50000 Franks, which the Duke <hi>de Longueville,</hi> diſtributed amongſt the ſouldiers; who thus encouraged with a generall vote teſtified their forwardneſſe to attend him in his future deſignes.</p>
               <p>The gaining of all theſe Forts brought not the <hi>French</hi> Generall to the period and end of his pains, but renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his labour, and proſecution of his Conqueſts. Towards <hi>Bleterans</hi> he tended, and to leave nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, which might be an Harbour to the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> he firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k in three ſmall Caſtles, that of <hi>Chaſteau-chalon,</hi> which ſubmitted <hi>Iuly</hi> 15/2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and the other at <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay,</hi> and <hi>Pica</hi> which came in <hi>Iuly</hi> 17/27, and then made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Saint <hi>Lawrence la Roche,</hi> one of the ſtrongeſt picces, and of moſt importance in that territory.</p>
               <p>An adviſo which hapned into his hands whileſt hee was at <hi>Chaſteau-chalon,</hi> made him leave the two laſt Forts, to the care of <hi>Montauſier</hi> the Camp-maſter, and march away with all ſpeed to beſiege that City. <hi>Iuly</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, A Letter was intercepted, which was to be carried by a <note place="margin">S. <hi>Lawrence la Roche,</hi> the town ſurprized by the <hi>French.</hi>
                  </note> peaſant from the Garriſon of the towne and Caſtle of Saint <hi>Lawrence</hi> to the Governour of <hi>Bleteran,</hi> the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port whereof was, that they deſired him to remit them their own Governour, becauſe the <hi>French</hi> Army drew towards them, and they were threatned with a ſpeedle ſiege. The Duke from hence collected, that if he could ſurround them before the return of their Commander, he might eaſily carry the place, the ſtrength of a Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not conſiſting ſo much upon the numbers of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary men and common Fortifications, as the ſage dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of an expert Leader, who armed with authority,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:178347:29"/> can both awe the men, and manage the action, To loſe no time, the ſame day he ſent away a party of 400 cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen men, drawn out of al the Regiments, under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Verſtot</hi> the Camp-maſter, who reaching thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame Evening, ſent away two of the Serjeants belonging to the Regiment of <hi>Normandy,</hi> and twentie <note place="margin">Burned by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> which flie into the Caſtle.</note> Souldiers to view it. The Officers did their parts care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, found it aſſaultable, and ſo reported it; the Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter applyes himſelf to their relation, plants his ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ladders, and at point of day, <hi>Iuly</hi> 14/24, tooke it by ſcalado, yet the Serjeants bought it with the loſſe of their own lives, and one of the ſouldiers. The town was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and expoſed to pillage, but the inhabitants and Garriſon retyring into the Caſtle, by caſting fire-balls upon their houſes, milked the aſſaylants hopes in their expected pillage, but doing them withall one pleaſure in their preſervation from the peſtilence, which then raged ſo furiouſly in the City, that there was ſcarce one houſe free. The Camp-maſter ſent with ſpeed to the Generall to informe him, of what had been done, who the ſame day hee received his intelligence <hi>July</hi> 15/25, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched thither with the Vicount <hi>d' Arpajoux,</hi> viewed the place, notwithſtanding three Faulcons ſhot diſcharged againſt him, planted the Regiment of <hi>Normandie</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">Where they are beſieged &amp; forced to yield.</note> the town wall, from whence they made their daily approches to the Caſtle being ſupported, and relieved by the other Regiments of the army ſucceſſively. Sixteen days ſiege the Caſtle held out, and then wanting water, and afflicted with poſtilence, yielded upon this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the ſouldiers 48 in number, the remaynder which had eſcaped the Sword and Peſtilence, ſhould depart with one Captain, and one Serjeant, and their wives, the Drum beating, and without baggage, and ſo be convayed to <hi>Bleterans.</hi> It was granted them, they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:178347:29"/> were diſmiſſed with a Convoy of 100 Muſquetiers, and 50 horſe to <hi>Bleterant,</hi> the inhabitants being made pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners of warre.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An unexperienced Navigator to avoid</hi> Scylla <hi>falls into</hi> Charybdis, <hi>one extremity drives unadviſed ſoules into a worſe, like the fiſh, which to avoid the frying pan, leaps into the fire:</hi> the true Hierogly phicke of theſe poore ſoules, which by leaving Saint <hi>Lawrence de la Roche,</hi> thought themſelves ſecured in the choice of <hi>Bleterans,</hi> whither they had a ſafe convoy, ſafe as for the way, not as for a ſure ſhelter, that being the next place of note, and ſtrength which the Duke meant to engirt with his Forces.</p>
               <p>Criticall prognoſticks of the iſſue preceded the Fate of that City, the <hi>French</hi> omitted to do nothing, which might be for their advantage, and the inhabitants admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all things which conduced to their own prejudice, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bleteran</hi> in danger of a ſiege.</note> the hearts of the inhabitants fayled them, the beſt and wealthieſt Citizens tooke up a reſolution to ſave their perſons, and beſt goods in <hi>Dole,</hi> and yet changed their counſell preſently, fearing what they had juſt cauſe to ſuſpect, to be ſurprized by the way, though they were to be conducted by a Convoy. The Count of <hi>Guebriant</hi> Field-marſhall to the Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> had notice of their firſt intention, by Letters intercepted from a peaſant, who was intruſted with that portage to <hi>Dole,</hi> &amp; leaving the Campeat <hi>Chilly, Auguſt</hi> 1/11, went to way-lay them. An ambuſcado hee prepared upon the way, expecting <note place="margin">The Burgeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes prepare to ſlie.</note> each minute the waggons which were to carry their wealth, liſtned after the Bels, and the Carters whiſtles, ſent out his Scouts to deſcry them, yet neither could the eyes of his Spies, nor his own diligent harkening bring him any aſſurance of his hope: They neither did, nor intended to ſtirre at that time; perplexed, knotty doubts
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:178347:30"/> had ſtaggered their reſolve, ſomething they meant to do, to that purpoſe, but neither knew, nor could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Guebriant</hi> way lays them, and they not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming abroad,</note> of the How or the When to do it ſecurely. <hi>Gue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briant</hi> would no longer attend the Citizens, but by a deviſe thought to inveagle the Garriſon, and draw the military men into the trap which hee had laid for the Burgeſſes; his party conſiſted of 200 light horſe, and 100 <hi>Dragoons,</hi> ten of his <hi>Cavaliers</hi> hee ſent abroad to ſurprize the Peaſants, which by night were imployed <note place="margin">Addreſſeth a ſtratagem to ſurprize the Garriſon. That failing he takes in <hi>Ioſſeau</hi> a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</note> to bring home the crop of the Earth: thinking by this means to make the ſouldiers iſſue out for their ſuccour, and ſo to entangle them: the <hi>French</hi> horſmen did their part, ſurprized thirty peaſants when they had loaden their horſes with corn, and by bright day light, deeming that the preſidiaries would come abroad to relieve and releaſe the Captives, marched with theſe priſoners hard by the Counter-ſcarpe. All this would not do, the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon ſent ſome Cannon-ſhot after them, but would not purſue them. The Count thus fruſtrated of his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, roſe from his ambuſh, and marched directly to the Caſtle of <hi>Iouſſeau,</hi> which he reached by noon, being but three leagues from <hi>Bleteran,</hi> and though it was a place of good ſtrength, rounded with a Moate foure perches broad, eight foot deep of water, flanked with four good towres, and fortified by a countermure, had it ſurrendred unto him at his firſt appearing, upon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. <hi>Where Valour and Counſell leads, Fortune attends, and crownes the deſigne with a prosperous iſſue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jouſſeau,</hi> by the change of the Lord, had ſome altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of its Lawes, a <hi>French</hi> Garriſon was preſently put into it, which muſt ſtand in oppoſition, to the townes with which the Caſtle lately had commerce and correſpondence, and that done, the Field-marſhall
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:178347:30"/> went to <hi>Loges</hi> another Fort within half a league of the <note place="margin">And the Fort <hi>de Loges,</hi>
                  </note> former, which he ſummoned, took in, and then prepared for his ſpeedy returne to the Army. But one raw mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, the fayling of his firſt project at <hi>Bleterans,</hi> was not yet digeſted, hee ſtill concluded that hee had done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worthy himſelfe in that expedition, if he did no <note place="margin">Addreſſeth a new ſtratagem for the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Blete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi>
                  </note> more; &amp; to allure the preſidiaries in <hi>Bleterans</hi> out of the town, hee marched in their open ſight with his army towards the Camp, leaving five or ſix <hi>Dragoons</hi> behind him, with inſtructions that when it might be imagined that the mayn body of his Forces were marched a two houres journey, they ſhould ariſe from the place where they lay hid, drive away all the cattle which were graſing neer the City, and if the Garriſon did purſue them, they ſhould with a ſecure, but not over-haſty pace, go on to ſuch a place, where hee would lay ſome <hi>Carabins</hi> to ſave them, and ſurprize the purſuing Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. The actions of his men, and the Event anſwered his directions. The <hi>Dragoons</hi> turned Drovers, and the Garriſon ſeeing the cattle which were their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance driven away, by that maniple of men, ſent out 40 horſe and 50 Muſquetiers to recover them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>Dragoons</hi> at the firſt drave on faire and gently, till they ſaw the bait had taken, and then mending their pace, <note place="margin">And ſurpriſed a part of the preſidiaries.</note> but obſerving ſuch a diſtance as might keep them out of the reach of the Enemies Muſquets, and give the purfuers hope to over-take them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> led them on to their Fate, the wood where <hi>Vilette</hi> lurked with his <hi>Carabins,</hi> which ſodainly and roundly fell upon them, and at the firſt charge, cut them all in pieces (but 15 who begged quarter, and obtained it, and five <hi>Cavallieres,</hi> whoſe Steeds ſtood them in more ſtead then their ſwords, and by their ſpeed ſaved their Riders, and themſelves in <hi>Bleterans.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:178347:31"/>
               <p> This atchievement, ſatisfied him for the preſent, he was well provided to give an account to the Generall of his doings, and now returned to the Campe then at <hi>Ruffey,</hi> where, before his comming in, the Duke of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bleterans</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged,</note> 
                  <hi>Longueville</hi> being re-enforced with 12 freſh Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Regiment <hi>de Caſtel-moron,</hi> had concluded to beſiege <hi>Bleterans,</hi> and had ſent <hi>Vandy</hi> the Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, and <hi>Marſin</hi> a new Colonell, raiſed to that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour by the death of the <hi>Liegois Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>queroy,</hi> which died of the plague at <hi>Chalon,</hi> with 60 Muſquetiers, and 200 men at armes, to burn down the Mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon the River, <note place="margin">and deſcribed.</note> which they did accordingly.</p>
               <p>The town is ſituated in the County of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> in figure ſquare, conſiſting of 600 Families, with one fair ſtreet, which extends it ſelfe from the Eaſt end to the Weſt, and many leſſer ſtreets, and lanes abutting upon it. A four-ſquare Caſtle, guarded with a double ditch, four great towres at the foure corners, and foure others upon the firme land betwixt the two Moats, ſtands like a Bulwarke at one Angle of the City, which being ſtrong by nature, built in the middle of a <hi>Mooraſſe,</hi> whither the Cannon could not have been drawn, had not the drought paved the ground, muſt now entertain theſe new gueſts which came to viſit it; it ſtood alone for the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> the neighbouring Forts and places of <note place="margin">The Caſtle of <hi>Fontenay</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred.</note> ſtrength, had ſubmitted to the Chriſtian King, <hi>Fontenay</hi> honoured ſtill by the birth of S. <hi>Bernhard,</hi> which held out laſt, being taken in by <hi>Guebriant,</hi> after three Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons ſhot againſt it.</p>
               <p>Some days were ſpent in intrenching the Army, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of batteries, making of Gabeonnadoes and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>Aug.</hi> 16/26, was the firſt day when the platforme of the ſiege was drawn, and <hi>Aug.</hi> 21/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1, the Duke having ſpent 600 Cannon-ſhot in the foure preceding days a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:178347:31"/> the walls, and made a breach of 25 paces in length firſt ſummoned the City, and the Garriſon at firſt demanding three dayes reſpite to acquaint the Lievtenant Generall of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> with the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of their eſtate, and upon the Generals deniall of <note place="margin">The town of <hi>Bleterans</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> their requeſt, telling him plainly that they were able to guard the breach, and would not yield, he concluded to aſſault it, and did ſo the ſame day, and carried it by force, maugre the reſiſtance of 300 <hi>Alman</hi> Souldiers, which lay therin, in whom the inhabitants put a ſtrange conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, for their valour ſhewed at <hi>Saverne,</hi> and in the fury put 200 men of the inhabitants, whom he found in armes to the ſword, but preſerved the lives and honours of 300 women which implored his grace, incloſing them in a Sanctuary, till the violence of the raging tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt was over.</p>
               <p>The Caſtle ſerved as a place of retreat to the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and held out till <hi>Sept.</hi> 2. new ſtile, when the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants <note place="margin">The beſieged ſlie to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, where they capitulate and ſurrender.</note> deſired to capitulate, ſent out an hoſtage to that effect, the Maſter of their Ordnance, received an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other from the Campe, <hi>Mico</hi> Lievtenant of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Anguien,</hi> and after much ſcruple, and many difficulties obtained theſe conditions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">I. THat the Souldiers ſhould have liberty to depart with their armes, baggage, one Dum beating, bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let in mouth, and lighted matches.</item>
                  <item n="2">II. That they might carry with them two field-peeces,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:178347:32"/> ſuch as ſhould be aſſigned them by the Duke of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueville.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="3">III. That they ſhould be furniſhed with waggons to tranſport their baggage, ſicke, and wounded men.</item>
                  <item n="4">IV. That they ſhould have a Convoy, with ſecurity to <hi>Dole.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Laſtly, that the inhabitants, which had retired into the Caſtle, ſhould freely go whither they pleaſed, and as many as would ſtay in the town, ſhould take an oath of allegeance to the Chriſtian King. All which were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and the Garriſon having ſtayed two dayes to pack up their trinkets, marched out <hi>Sept.</hi> 5, new ſtile, 300 in all the moſt <hi>Almans,</hi> which took ſervice under the <hi>French,</hi> and the other <hi>Comtois,</hi> who according to the treaty, were conducted to <hi>Dole,</hi> by 150 <hi>French Cavalliers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:178347:32"/>
               <head>The Actions and Occurrences in <hi>Piemont, Montferrat, Millanois,</hi> and generally throughout <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He departure of the Duke <hi>de Rohan,</hi> from the <hi>Valtoliue,</hi> not only promoted the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> deſignes among the <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and <hi>Valteliuers,</hi> the <hi>Griſons</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging <note place="margin">Troubles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Griſons</hi> after <hi>Rohans</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> a juriſdiction over the <hi>Valteli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> which they deny, and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Leganez,</hi> Governour of <hi>Millain,</hi> fiſhing in thoſe troubled waters, interpoſing as a ſtickler in that controverſie, which is not yet agreed of, but ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Marqueſſes hands againſt the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> in the Principality of <hi>Piemont</hi> and <hi>Montferrat,</hi> his united forces of 20000 foot, and 5000 horſe (becauſe there was no Enemy to flank him) being brought down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Duke, before the <hi>French</hi> ſuccours under the command of <hi>Crequy,</hi> could be brought in to his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. The Dukes Army which ſhould make head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> hoaſt, was but a ſmall one, 5000 foot and 1500 horſe, yet ſo well diſpoſed and ordered, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:178347:33"/> with this ſmall number hee guarded his Dominions, from that univerſall devaſtation which threatned them <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leganez</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Millain</hi> goeth into the field.</note> though with loſſe of ſome places, till the <hi>French</hi> came in to relieve him. <hi>Leganez</hi> appearing in field at <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varra, Iune</hi> 6 new ſtile, <hi>Grequy</hi> not reaching the Duke till <hi>Iune</hi> 14/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4, eighteen days after, when hee arrived op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunely at <hi>Caſſall,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Marqueſſe, before the <hi>French</hi> came in, having threatned to beſiege it.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Novarra</hi> the Marqueſſe divided his Army into three parts, one was to ſtay with him here, the ſecond was ſent into the <hi>Lomeline;</hi> and the third under <hi>Gildas</hi> towards <hi>Niſſe de la Paille,</hi> which was the firſt place <note place="margin">The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army is divi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded into three parts.</note> he aimed at; the victory there being prepared for him before his comming, by the trechery of the inhabitants, who by private intelligences, had invited him to come before it, and promiſed to ſurrender it, in deſpight of the Governour and the Garriſon. A traitor in a State is like a Serpent in the boſome, fatall if foſtered, and unremoved. The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> knew not the ſecret practice betwixt thoſe Rebels and his Enemies, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded them as ſubjects, and was carefull for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. Vpon the firſt bruit of <hi>Gildas</hi> his comming downe, he diſpatcht thither wards, two companies of light horſe, one conſiſting of 80, and the other of 40 <hi>Cavalliers,</hi> who came into the town, <hi>May</hi> 31, <hi>June</hi> 10 before day, and receiving intelligence, that the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> were then at <hi>Anciſa</hi> a place faſt by, ſent out ſome Vant-curriers to diſcover their number and poſture, who returning with an anſwer, that the Army conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of 4000 foot, 1200 horſe, and ſome <hi>Dragoons,</hi> theſe <hi>Cavallieres</hi> reſolved to viſit them, and skirmiſhed <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gildas</hi> ſent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Niſſe le p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> with them all that day, being ſecured from much da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage by the Canons of the towne, which played ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageouſly upon the Campe, and at night were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:178347:33"/> into the City by the Governour, who diſpoſed them into their ſeverall places to defend the City. The night nurſing mother of thoſe deeds of darkneſſe, firſt cauſed the evill affection of the Citizens towards the Duke their lawfull Prince to be ſuſpected, when <hi>Gildas</hi> aſſaulting an half-moon neer the Cloyſter of the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins,</hi> carried it by the ſlackneſſe of the defendants, who inclining to his party, did as good as ſurrender it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out oppoſing him, and ſuffered his <hi>Cavallary</hi> and <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons</hi> to paſſe the River of <hi>Borbo,</hi> and range themſelves in Battalia upon Saint <hi>Francis</hi> his Hill, and the day en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing plainly diſcovered it. The preſidiaries did their beſt, both for their owne defence and offence of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaylants: They skirmiſhed all day, neere the <hi>Piemont</hi> Port, with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Campe, to give the inhabitants opportunity to go abroad to get forage for the horſes, of which they were almoſt deſtitute. Out they went, but did little to help their friends at home, and much for the advantage of thoſe new ones abroad, <hi>Gildas</hi> were certified by ſome of them, of the eſtate of the towne more particularly, and ſent a Scout of ſummons to yield before that <hi>Leganez</hi> came downe directed to the Governour, and the Lord Saint <hi>Paul</hi> then reſiding <note place="margin">Summoneth the City.</note> there by a trumpet, accompanied with two <hi>Capuchins,</hi> and the Curate of Saint <hi>John de Niſſe,</hi> (who fained himſelfe to have been a priſoner to the <hi>Spaniard)</hi> to which the Governour returned no other anſwer, but that hee thanked <hi>Gildas,</hi> and would prepare to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Leganez</hi> in a military bravery, with this anſwere the Drum, and the two <hi>Capuchins</hi> returned, but the Curat ſtayed behind, to adde more ſuell to that fire of mutiny, which was kindled in the City, and to paſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of each circumſtance to the <hi>Spaniſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Army. The baſeſt of creatures are moſt proliſicous, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:178347:34"/> animals produce more yong ones in number, and in a farre ſhorter time, then the perfect; the ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <note place="margin">Which by the treachery and ſeditious pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants,</note> Curate had prepared aſpeech, a ſhort one ſcarce of three lines, to divide the hearts of people from their Prince, and it wrought ſo effectually, that the Drum had ſcarce delivered his anſwer to <hi>Gildas,</hi> and he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to aſſault the Curtain of Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> when the rebellion of the people (which like fire, if it fall upon flaxe, or ſuch combuſtible matter, doth ſoone rayſe it ſelf to a flame) at firſt aſhamed to ſhew its head, fed with the oily words of a traiterous Prieſt, began to be both inſolent and impudent, they abandoned the ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to which they were deſigned, threatned the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyards</hi> Officers to deliver them into the hands of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> unleſſe they would preſently capitulate, 40 of them marching up to the Governour, with menaces to murder him, unleſſe he did treat inſtantly. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander ſeeing how hee was preſt betwixt two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes, apparant danger of life, if he ſhould refuſe, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominie if he ſhould aſſent, though to ſpin out the time <note place="margin">Was ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,</note> a little, till he could pacifie this commotion, ſent out a Drum, as if he meant to Article, and in lieu of him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Serjeant from the Campe, ſo obtaining a ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of armes, which he ſpent with all remonſtrances he could think of, to pacifie the people, and divert them <note place="margin">In deſpight of the Governour and garriſon.</note> from that ſhamefull revolt, when not prevailing with the inraged multitude, he was forced to come to cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and <hi>Iune</hi> 4/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4, the Garriſon of 300 men (able to have maintained the place againſt the enemie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, if there had not been a worſe within) departed from the City, and left it to the command of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Breme</hi> was the next place, deſigned by the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Marqueſſe to be conquered by his forces, and a deſigne
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:178347:34"/> only it was, which never came to execution, it being a place of ſtrength well garriſoned, and provided for by the Duke of <hi>Savoy, Emery</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador, and <hi>Praſtin</hi> who laid in an experienced, couragious ſouldier <hi>Mont-gaillard</hi> to defend it, and that being known to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generall, he loth to ſpend his time and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces there, which might be imployed elſwhere more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditiouſly left it, and with his Army firſt beſieged <hi>Aglian</hi> or <hi>Aillan,</hi> a Caſtle neere <hi>Aſti,</hi> ſituate upon an Hill, where <hi>Renato Roero,</hi> which commanded there, received him couragiouſly, hanging up a black flag, in teſtimony that he meant to hold it, as long as hee was <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Agliano</hi> beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
                  </note> able, his deeds anſwering the outward ſigne wherby he expreſt his reſolution.</p>
               <p>Severall times he aſſaulted it, and was as oft repelled, with more loſſe in concluſion, then glory by the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quution: the way he went, proclaimed the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to be a man of undaunted courage, fit for the managing of ſuch an enterprize, three vollies of the ſhafts of fate, winged with rage, and pointed with death, could not divert him from following his enterprize, nor the fourth <note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth divers aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults,</note> more dreadfull then any of the former appale him; twenty wagons were laden with men, wounded in this laſt attempt; the Hoſpitals of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Miſſe</hi> were filled with Creples, diſmembred, impotent men: ſome Commanders of note were ſlaine out-right, the Colonell <hi>Lion</hi> a <hi>German,</hi> the Serjeant Major <hi>Crevelli,</hi> three Captains, 15 Lievtenants, and <hi>Alfieres,</hi> beſides a man of more ſpeciall rank, known to be ſuch by his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, not his name, and yet all this misfortune could not ſhake, much leſſe ſhatter his grounded reſolution: The <note place="margin">Slaughters upon the aſſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants.</note> Marqueſſe was not in the ſiege perſonally, and yet was preſent there powerfully, his quarter was then at <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtighliote,</hi> betwixt <hi>Nave</hi> and <hi>Caſtignone,</hi> places late ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:178347:35"/> to the <hi>Savoyard,</hi> but now ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed by the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Army, being but open Dorps, Towres unfortified, and there informed of the former ill ſucceſſe, concluded of another way to compaſſe his deſigne. The Caſtle was by his direction undermined in two ſeveral places, and that neer the <hi>Aſtiſan</hi> Port was ſprung, <hi>June</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, more fortunately for the beſieged, then the aſlaylants, theſe being covered and ſmothered with the earth, which fell upon them, thoſe having an halfmoon which defended the Caſtle neer it, better fortified by a new mount of earth, raiſed by the playing of that mine, then it had bin formerly.</p>
               <p>Yet all this only deferred, prevented not the fate of the Citadell. A new aſſault was concluded, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken the next day, which though for that time was <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Agliano</hi> taken by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards.</hi>
                  </note> beaten off, with a notable loſſe to the aſſailants, ſo abated both the ſpirits, and number of the defendants, that within two dayes having then endured a ſiege of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days, (begun with reſolution to maſter the Fort, and continued without ceſſation of hoſtile oppoſition) were compelled to condition for their lives, and the Commander and Officers being dimitted with their ſwords by their ſides, and the ſouldiers with white ſtaves, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Marqueſſe intending to demoliſh the Caſtle which he had purchaſed with the loſſe of 3000 of his men, ſlain and disbanded, that it might no more ſteed the <hi>Savoyard</hi> his adverſary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gold may be bought too deare:</hi> ſo was <hi>Agliamo,</hi> the Marqueſſe after this prize, aymed at an higher pitch of Glory, but could not reach it, the wings of his Army by which he was to mount being clipped by the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ancy of the <hi>Savoyards,</hi> &amp; the Duke hanging like a plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met at his heels, to pull him downwards when he was riſing. <hi>Albe</hi> was menaced with a ſiege, but that was
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:178347:35"/> ſtrongly garriſoned with 3000 ſouldiers, and the Duke incamped himſelf with his ſmall Army, neer the bridge <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Legauez</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp neere each other.</note> upon the <hi>Taner,</hi> to hinder the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generall from rayſing a banke againſt it: which cauſed the Marqueſſe about the end of <hi>Iune</hi> to retreat towards his own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, the <hi>Millanez,</hi> paſſing the River under the ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Fort <hi>de Nom,</hi> and to incampe in a ſmall field betwixt <hi>Ancona</hi> and <hi>Aſti,</hi> neere the <hi>Taner,</hi> labouring unceſſantly about his Trenches, to earth himſelf within ſo ſmall a diſtance of his Highneſſe, whoſe little Army lay fortified in the wombe of its common mother, <hi>the Ground,</hi> that the Sentinels could parlee together, as they did frequently.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Strength is not the only thing that makes a ſouldier vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious: He that carried a ſpeare like a Weavers beam, was vanquiſhed by a ſtripling:</hi> preſumption of the power of his brawny arms, was the bane of that ſuperlatively ſtrong Crotoniate, and the Marqueſſe his conſidence in the number, and force of his <hi>Cavallary,</hi> expoſed his horſmen both to danger and damage. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> horſe it firſt were enquartered without his Trenches, the Duke perceived how open they lay aſſaulted them, and forced them to ſeek a more ſecure ſtation. But what aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance <note place="margin">The Marques his horſes quartered without his trenches are expoſed to da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</note> of ſafety is there amongſt the many turns, and doubtfull changes of warre? The ditches and mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walled ſtables whither they retreated, might ſhelter them from the <hi>Savoyards</hi> ſword, but not from famine. Graſſe did not grow in the new opened bowels of the earth, but upon the ſurface, the beaſts muſt abroad to fetch in their forrage, or periſh, and their Riders to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for them, made many incurſions into <hi>Montferrat,</hi> whence they ſtill came ſhort home, the Dukes <hi>Carabins</hi> which hee had planted there to guard that Province, cutting off the men, which adventured to get food for the Cattell.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:178347:36"/>
               <p> Hitherto the balls were but toſſed, which afterwards came to be banded. The vigilant <hi>Spaniard</hi> lay cloſe at his defenſive ward, &amp; would not offer to make a blow til he thought he might do it certainly, and ſtrike home: His Highneſſe (as it behoved him) was no leſſe caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous then his Enemy: Both lay upon their advantages, though with ſome difference of their ends, the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> ayming to winne ground from his Highneſſe, the Duke who all this while laboured only to ſecure his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion from that forrain invaſion.</p>
               <p>The Marqueſſe perceived that the Duke grew daily more and more ſtrong, and therupon imagined, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all his Forces were generally drawne into the <hi>Aſteſan,</hi> that the other part of the Country was unfurniſhed of men, and therfore ſelecting 4000 Foot, and 500 Horſe, out of the mayn body of his army, ſent them with three <note place="margin">The Prince of <hi>Modena</hi> ſent into <hi>Langues,</hi>
                  </note> peeces of Cannon, under the command of the Prince <hi>Borſio</hi> of <hi>Modena</hi> to <hi>Langues,</hi> who razed <hi>Montbaldo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Reccaveran</hi> whence the inhabitants were fled, and burnt all the Villages as farre as <hi>Courtenville,</hi> which was deſigned for the fire too, but bought its ſafety with a ſumme of money. The Prince finding ſuch a naked Country ſo farre, thought to finde all the reſt unprovl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded both of men and munition, ſent back his Cannon, which he would not ſtay to lugge after him, to make <note place="margin">Plundereth the territory.</note> the more ſpeed, and in haſte came before <hi>Salietto,</hi> which the inhabitants had forſaken, but was then (the day before the Princes comming) garriſoned with 150 <hi>Dragoons,</hi> by the provident care of his Highneſſe, who alſo commanded the whole Regiment of <hi>Senantes,</hi> which till then was laid in <hi>Albe,</hi> to march thither alſo, and to be aſſiſtant to that ſmall Garriſon againſt the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy. The proceſſe of all this was made known to the Prince <hi>Bórſio,</hi> who now miſſing the Canon, of which
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:178347:36"/> he had disburdened his Army, and being once repulſed, when he intended to have ſurprized the place by ſcala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, marched thence immediately againſt the Caſtle <hi>Santa Iulia,</hi> which being defended but by 50 men, and <note place="margin">Taketh in the Fort <hi>Santa Iulia.</hi>
                  </note> undermined in two ſeverall places by the Prince his pioners, in the night was ſurrendred the next day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>Senantes,</hi> who was ordered by the Duke to keep an eye upon the Prince his deſignes, could ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to his Friends with his auxiliary Forces. The Commiſſion given to the <hi>Savoyard</hi> Colonell was to attend upon the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and to impeach him, as much as might be, with the ſecurity of his Regiment, which was then only of 500 men, but not to adventure the hazard of a battaile, in regard of the diſparity betwixt his, and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> forces. The Colonel obſerved the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to which he was limited, and concealing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Campe, which lay about <hi>Santa Iulia,</hi> lodged himſelfe upon the top of a Mountain till <note place="margin">Where he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campeth and is raiſed by <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes,</hi> a Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell to the D. of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
                  </note> midnight, when riſing ſuddenly, he fell upon one of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> quarters unexpectedly, ſlue above 200 men up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the place, took one Captain and ſome Officers, and ſouldiers, priſoners of warre, and brought ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed amazement upon the whole <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Campe, that the Prince <hi>Borſio</hi> diſcamped preſently, and retired in ſome diſorder, by the way of <hi>Cairo,</hi> being purſued three <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles by <hi>Senantes,</hi> who then returning met with another <hi>Savoyard</hi> Colonell <hi>Cerruto,</hi> who by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from his Highneſſe, joyned his troops to thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Senantes,</hi> to ſtop the progreſſe of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> if hee ſhould hap to appeare againe in the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leganez</hi> in the <hi>interim,</hi> mployed himſelfe to build a Fort Royal at <hi>Rocca,</hi> point-blank againſt that at <hi>Anone,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">A Fort Royall built by <hi>Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nez</hi> at <hi>Rocca.</hi>
                  </note> wherin he uſed ſuch diligence, that beſides the great
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:178347:37"/> number of Pioners and Maſons, which he had muſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the State of <hi>Millan,</hi> to that purpoſe, he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered two Companies of each Regiment to helpe the ordinary labourers in the ſpeedy raiſing of that fortified building. He performed it happily, and was therby ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured againſt both the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Savoyards</hi> forces, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ready to joyn if he had not bin neceſſitated through want of forrage and victuals. The penury of his men, pinched them more, then the hoſtile actions of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary. Many would faine have run away from their colours, if the wayes had been open for their ſlight, the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leganez</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campeth.</note> Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> perceived it, and obſerving the old rule, that it is wiſdome to lay a bridge of gold for a flying Enemy, opened the paſſages to <hi>Montferrat,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were blocked up, relieved the Fugitives which fled from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Campe, both with meat and money, and by this means did more ſcath to <hi>Leganez,</hi> then hee could have done by all mights the Marqueſſe ſeeing his Army abated every day, and himſelfe vexed in his tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, by the frequent aſſaults made by his Highneſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camping and retiring under the ſafegard of his Forts towards the territory of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> relinquiſhing <hi>Piemont</hi> and <hi>Montferrat,</hi> when he had fortified <hi>Agli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ano,</hi> and <hi>Niſſe de la Paille,</hi> lately gotten from the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this the <hi>French</hi> ſuccours were come in, and one part of them under the Count <hi>de Verrue,</hi> was imployed to aſſiſt <hi>Cerruto</hi> &amp; <hi>Senantes,</hi> againſt the Prince of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dena,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>French</hi> Army joynes with the D. of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who ſends a part therof againſt the Prince of <hi>Modena.</hi>
                  </note> who with fire &amp; ſword made havock in <hi>Langues</hi> and the other part under the <hi>French</hi> Generall, the Duke <hi>de Crequy,</hi> was tranſmitted to his Highneſſe, to attend upon the deſignes of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Marqueſſe. <hi>Verrue</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his charge ſo well, that he chaſed <hi>Borſio</hi> out of <hi>Langues,</hi> became maſter of the Towne and Caſtle of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:178347:37"/> 
                  <hi>Carchere,</hi> (a place of much importance, being the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from <hi>Piemout</hi> to <hi>Genoa,</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> by which the <hi>French Curriers</hi> could not formerly paſſe without much perill) having firſt ſurprized the greateſt part of that Garriſon in the open field, put the one half to the ſword, the remaynder flying to the Mountains for their preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and afterwards beſieged <hi>Cairo,</hi> a place of ſtrength in <hi>Langues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſervice done by the Count and his aſſiſtants, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelan,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cairo</hi> beſieged by <hi>Verrue.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cerruto</hi> and <hi>Seuantes,</hi> was no leſſe offenſive to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> then gratefull to the Chriſtian King, and the Duke his Conſederate, <hi>Leganez</hi> to divert <hi>Verrue</hi> from proſequuting the ſiege of <hi>Cayre,</hi> brought his forces out of the territory of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> over the <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> into the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Legenez</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vades <hi>Vercel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lois.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vercellois,</hi> and burned certain Villages there, thinking to compell the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to recall <hi>Verrue</hi> to aſſiſt him with the <hi>French</hi> troops, and ſo make him leave off the ſiege which he had happily begun, and was like to finiſh fortunately.</p>
               <p>But the project took not, <hi>Verrue</hi> took in the place &amp; ſtirred not till he had done it. His Highneſſe was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely adviſed of the Marqueſſes march and purpoſe, and would not revoke the order he had given the <hi>Count de</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">But his project takes not.</note> 
                  <hi>Verrue,</hi> thinking himſelf ſtrong enough (being now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enforced with the reſt of the <hi>French</hi> troops) to meet the enemie in <hi>Campania,</hi> but preſently ſent the Marqueſſe of <hi>Pianeſſa,</hi> to muſter up all the <hi>Cavallary</hi> neere <hi>Vercelle,</hi> and to enquarter them in ſuch a place, where hee might moſt conveniently intangle the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> forces, and ſtay them in their full careere: himſelfe in the mean time vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting the territories of <hi>Verrue, Creſſentin,</hi> and <hi>Trin,</hi> and lodging that night neere the bridge at <hi>Sture;</hi> His ſtay there miniſtred an occaſion of a combat betwixt his and the <hi>French</hi> united forces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> army, under
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:178347:38"/> 
                  <hi>Don Martino de Arragon, Tiberio</hi> of <hi>Naples, Lucio Boc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capiana, Don Giovanni Cavalla</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Camp-maſter, the Count <hi>Bolognino</hi> Lievtenant Generall of the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, <hi>Don Fedro</hi> Commiſſary Generall of the <hi>Cavallary, Spaden</hi> and other Officers. It was thus! At <hi>Sture</hi> his Highnes was informed, that theſe <hi>Spaniſh Cavalliers</hi> with one part of the Army, had order to ravage the Lands of the Prince of <hi>Maſſeran,</hi> upon whom they meant to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge themſelves, becauſe that he the yeere laſt paſt had driven them out of <hi>Crev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oeur</hi> which they had unjuſtly detained from him, and afterwards to make an invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the <hi>Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lois;</hi> where they meant to plunder the Country, as they had done the <hi>Aſteſan,</hi> and the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lois,</hi> and to prevent them; he diſpatched the Marqueſſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illa,</hi> Generall of his Horſe and Field-marſhall of the Chriſtian Kings Army to go and joyn ſome companies of Horſe with thoſe under the Marqueſſe of <hi>Pianeſſa</hi> about <hi>Verſelle,</hi> and take an opportunity to fight with the <note place="margin">A battaile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ille,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> forces neer <hi>Ceſia.</hi>
                  </note> Enemy. The Marqueſſe followed his direction, and par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing from the Campe then at <hi>Morani, Iuly</hi> 21, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> 1, with his troops making about 1300 Horſe, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to <hi>Verſelli</hi> about 11 of the clock, where he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that one part of the Enemy was already paſſed over the River of <hi>Ceſia,</hi> having carried away out of the <hi>Verſellois</hi> a booty of cattell, and taken priſoner the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Eſprit,</hi> Lievtenant of the <hi>Carabins,</hi> of <hi>Don Carlo,</hi> as he was ſcouring that Country with 20 of his men, five wherof they flue, and cauſed the reſt to flie. The report ſtartled the Marqueſſe, who ſeeing ſome other <hi>Spaniſh</hi> troops upon the further banke of the River, made over the ſtream toward them with his <hi>Cavallary,</hi> and ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted them, that they preſently fled, &amp; ſheltred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves behind the Fort of <hi>Doval,</hi> whither the Marqueſſe would not follow them, the Cannons being planted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:178347:38"/> his Army, and the Muſquetiers being ready to diſcharge upon him from the Fort, but returned toward the River, where hee was ſcarce arrived, but he perceived (within an houre) ſome troops of <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Horſe, making in all about 1500, marching toward <note place="margin">Begun by a light skirmiſh.</note> him with a prety hand-gallop, as prepared to fight with him who ſtood ready to entertain them. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat began in a light skirmiſh betwixt the conjoyned <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Piemontain Dragoons</hi> and <hi>Carrabins,</hi> and thoſe of the Enemy, but laſted not long, being broken off, by the comming in of a new Squadron of <hi>French</hi> Horſe, which charged this Avantguard of the Spaniſh Army ſo furiouſly, that they were preſently routed, and put to flight. The Spaniſh Battalia ſtood whole ſtill, whither the Avantguard ſled, and were rallied to renew <note place="margin">Comes to a pitcht battail, which a while continued doubtfull,</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> freſh combat, which laſted doubtfull on both ſides, till the Squadron of <hi>Souvray</hi> breaking in amongſt the middeſt of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> broke their ranks, and defeated them intirely, having ſlain betwixt three and four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred upon the place, and taken as many priſoners, the moſt of them Officers, and men of quality. Amongſt the dead were found <hi>Lucio Boccapiana,</hi> Camp-maſter, one Marqueſſe of <hi>Davie,</hi> the Lievtenant of the Colonell <hi>Sehic;</hi> the Provoſt Marſhall of the <hi>German</hi> Forces; two Lievtenants, three Cornets, and many other Officers which are unknown. <hi>Don Martino</hi> of <hi>Arragon</hi> eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped hardly, his horſe being ſlaine under him, and hee beaten to the ground: <hi>Don Antonio</hi> Nephew to the Count of <hi>Montery</hi> Viceroy of <hi>Naples, Spadin</hi> and many other <note place="margin">Yet in the end the <hi>French</hi> get the victory.</note> Officers and men of quality being taken priſoners.</p>
               <p>During the time of this combat, the Count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>errue</hi> took in the City of <hi>Cairo,</hi> and went from thence to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlege <hi>Larocca</hi> neer <hi>Aſti:</hi> lately fortified by <hi>Leganez,</hi> in the time of his abode there. The Marqueſſe had then a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:178347:39"/> time of ſorrows which thronged together upon him. A Currier came from <hi>Spain</hi> with unwelcome news of his wives death, ſiſter to the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola,</hi> and another with a report of a new Succeſſor into his Government, yet neither of theſe did ſo much trouble him as the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and hopefull progreſſe of the united <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Piemontain</hi> Armies; the firſt hee knew to be a debt to Nature, and it did not trouble him, the other he thought might be falſe and raiſed by the malice of ſome of his enemies in Court, or, if true, yet he would take care to diſcharge his Office conſcionably, and comfort him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the true account, he ſhould make to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like King. <hi>La Rocca</hi> was beſieged, and he encouraged <note place="margin">
                     <hi>La Rocca</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Piemontains.</hi>
                  </note> the defendants to hold out manfully, promiſing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them as ſoon as he might conveniently. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants behaved themſelves manfully, being animated by the daily intelligence they received from their aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates, by the favour of a Hill upon the bank of <hi>Taner,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Generall to debarre them of that conference, commanded the Colonell <hi>Dallot</hi> to poſſeſſe himſelfe of that place: it was a worke of difficultie and danger, the Muſquetadoes played upon him from within, and the appointed ſuccours withſtood his way without, yet he performed it with as much happineſſe as valour.</p>
               <p>It was a work full of hazard, yet his induſtry joyned with Fortune overcame it, with much difficulty he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched himſelfe neere the palliſadoes of the beſieged, foure days together endured the ſallies of the Garriſon, and the aſſaults of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Campe, both which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">A notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit done by <hi>Dallot</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Colonell.</note> the benefit of a Mill, where the Enemy had flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cout'd himſelfe, and a woodden bridge laid over the River for their mutuall correſpondence. <hi>Dallot</hi> reſolved to burn them both, &amp; to that end putting off his clothes himſelfe, his brother, and two other ſouldiers good
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:178347:39"/> ſwimmers caſt themſelves into the River in the view of the Enemy, who played upon them with their Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, but hit them not, Fortune ſo favouring them, that they broke downe the doores of the Mill with the pickaxes which they carried in their belts, and burnt both that and the bridge with the balls of fire which they had in their hands, and left not the water until they ſaw them both conſumed into aſhes. The Marqueſſe of <hi>Leganez</hi> (conjecturing at the iſſue of this adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leganiz</hi> ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Don Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> to relieve <hi>la Rocca.</hi>
                  </note> began to feare that <hi>la Rocca</hi> could not hold out, and therupon diſcamping, returned into the State of <hi>Millan,</hi> where he drew out ſeven Regiments of foot, and 2000 Horſe from his Army, and ſent them under the conduct of the Marqueſſe <hi>Don Martin, d' Arragon</hi> to relieve it. His Highneſſe had notice of his march, and followed him. His ſpeedy purſuit after him brought him upon the Vantguard of <hi>Don Martin,</hi> conſiſting of 200 <hi>Dragoons</hi> and <hi>Carrabines,</hi> whom hee aſſaulted ſo roughly, that he ſlue and wounded moſt part of them, and put the reſt to flight. The iſſue made the <hi>Spaniſh Don</hi> to give over his deſigne, till <hi>Leganez</hi> with the main body of his Army might come in to his ſuccour. The Marqueſſe had ſpeedy intelligence of what had paſſed, and as ſpeedily came up to him, encamped upon the banke of <hi>Taner,</hi> with four peeces of Canon to impeach the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Piemountain</hi> Armies, who had pitched their Campe upon the declining of the Hill neer the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <note place="margin">The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Vantguard ſurprized. <hi>Legonez</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his whole Army againſt the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Piemontains.</hi>
                  </note> In fine, the Canons began to play on both ſides, &amp; thence (the Battalia's drawing neerer each other) the ſmall ſhot began to flie, and was ſpent ſo effectually, that for a time both ſides appeared loſers, and neither could promiſe it ſelfe a victory. Both Commanders and ordinary men fell down dead in both the Armies, till the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> a little declining the battaile, if either party
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:178347:40"/> was the gainer, it is thought to be the <hi>Savoyards</hi> Army. Many of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Chieftains fell that day, among <note place="margin">A battel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vi ctory.</note> which was a yonger brother of the Prince <hi>Borſio de Modenn,</hi> the certain number of the common men is not known, only 600 dead corpſes were reported by the priſoners to be tumbled into the River, and thirty waggons loaden with the carcaſſes of the principall men which were ſlaine, and ſome wounded ſouldiers were knowne to be ſent to <hi>Alexandria.</hi> Nor could the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Piemontain</hi> army glory of this conqueſt, it coſt them deare, the lives of many of their Officers and Souldiers, nor did the loſſe of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> do him ſo much prejudice, but that by the helpe of his Canon at <hi>Annona,</hi> and ſome companies of Muſquetiers (whom he afterwards ſent to guard the River) hee laid in 600 <note place="margin">The ſiege of <hi>la Rocca</hi> raiſed.</note> freſh men into <hi>la Rocca,</hi> who defended themſelves ſo bravely, that at laſt the ſiege was raiſed, and the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> was forced to depart without a Conqueſt.</p>
               <p>A victory ſoon after attended him, the <hi>French</hi> Fleet ſomewhat affrighted all the Sea-townes of <hi>Italy,</hi> and the Governour of <hi>Millam</hi> to ſecure the Catholique Kings townes upon the Sea-coaſt of <hi>Montferrat, Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> the ſecond new ſtile, drew out of his army 7000 footmen, <hi>Almayus, Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> ſix Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of horſe, and ſome companies of Harquebuzen horſmen, who under the command of the Prince of <hi>Modena, Don Martin d' Arragon,</hi> and <hi>Gildas</hi> with Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, <note place="margin">The victory gotten by the D. of <hi>Savoy</hi> at <hi>Monbaldon.</hi>
                  </note> Petards, Bombards, and Morterers had order to paſſe through <hi>Languez</hi> towards the Sea-coaſt, and, by the way to ſelze upon the Caſtle of <hi>Cengio,</hi> a place which his Highneſſe of <hi>Savoy</hi> had lately fortified. The Duke was informed of the Enemy his deſigne, and to overtake him <hi>September</hi> the fourth new ſtile, advanced as farre as <hi>Salycotte,</hi> within a league and halfe of <hi>Cengio,</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:178347:40"/> where underſtanding, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of his arrival, and becauſe they found <hi>Cengio</hi> newly reen forced with a garriſon of 200 men) were returning the way they came, he made after them, overtook them neere <hi>Mombaldon</hi> and the Valley of <hi>Espin</hi> upon the banke of <hi>Bor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io</hi> gave them battail, <hi>September</hi> the eighth new ſtile, and obtained ſuch a victory, that of thoſe 7000 Foot, and 1200 Horſe, not above 2000 eſcaped, the reſt being ſlain, or diſperſed upon the Mountains, where the Peaſants of the Country purſued them with all hoſtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y, and ſlue as many as they found. Beſides the loſſe of men 40 waggons loadeh with baggage, and 30 with amunition became a prey to the united Armies of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> to the great weakning of <hi>Leganez</hi> his Army, who to re-enforce it returned into the <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanez,</hi> and commanded each Family to ſupply him with a man.</p>
               <p>The news of this victory ecchoed through <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> the Marqueſſe of Saint <hi>German,</hi> Maſter of the Wardrobe to his Highneſſe, was ſent to the Chriſtian King with tydings of that ſucceſſe, and was there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained with ſuch ſtate as became his perſon &amp; office, <hi>Thur in</hi> re-ecchoed with the praiſes of the Duke, to whoſe vigiſancy they aſcribed this Fortune, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants had made bon-fires of joy, had not this For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne happineſſe been over-clouded with ſome ſorrow at home. The Ducheſse and her ſecond ſonne the Prince <hi>Emanuel</hi> were both ſick; and their maladies made the Citizens to ſympathize of their griefe. The Duke was informed of the ſtate of his Ducheſſe, and poſted from the Campe to viſit her, where after two days ſtay finding her recovered, hee returned into the <hi>Aſteſan</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Crequy,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Emry</hi> Embaſsadour to his Majeſtie of <hi>France,</hi> and the other Commanders, to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:178347:41"/> adviſe about the further proceedings of his Army. A Councell was called, neer the River <hi>Ceſia,</hi> and the Duke (though known to be ſage in Counſell, both for warre and peace) then ſeemed to out-ſtrip himſelf, when ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly a Collick paſſion tooke him, which firſt chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">The death of the Duke of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
                  </note> into a ſingle Tertian, and afterwards into a double, accompanied with ſome malignity, held him 11 days, till nature being overcome by the diſeaſe, there follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſeparation of ſoule and body in the one and fiftieth yeer of his age: A Prince hee was doubtleſſe of a great ſpirit, wiſe in policy, valiant and painfull in warre, and in demonſtrance of his affection to the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> and his Ducheſſe a ſiſter thereof, made her protectreſſe of his Children, and Regent of the State.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtian King (as ill news hath ſwift wings) had ſpeedier notice of the death of his brother in Law, than he had of the late victory, and to ſhew that his love was permanent after his death (according to the cuſtome of <note place="margin">The King of <hi>France</hi> cauſeth the Maſter of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</note> the <hi>Roman</hi> Church) gave order for a ſolemne <hi>Requiem,</hi> and a Dirge to be held in the Cathedrall at <hi>Paris</hi> with all ſolemnity. To this purpoſe, <hi>Le Sieur de Sainct tot,</hi> Maſter of the Ceremonies had order to command the Parliament and other Soveraigne Courts, the Provoſt of the Merchants and Sheriffs, the Rector and Scholars of the Vniverſity of <hi>Paris</hi> to ſuffragate at the Prayers and Service which his Majeſty had appointed in the Cathedrall of that City, giving him a Commiſſion to that purpoſe, dated at Saint <hi>Germans, October</hi> 14/24. The Maſter of the Ceremonies, according to his warrant the 16/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6, of the ſame moneth, in the Robes of his Office, <note place="margin">To proclaime an Office for his ſoule.</note> with a ſquare Cap upon his head clothed in a mourning Gown, with a train of four ells long, carried by foure Gentlemen, accompanied with three Heralds of Arms,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:178347:41"/> bearing in their hands their ſtaves of Office, which were garniſhed with ſlowre de Luces, then covered with Cypreſle, inveſted alſo in long black Robes, upon which they had their ordinary Coats of Velvet em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broydered with ſlowre de Luces, and attended with 23 ordinary Cryers of <hi>Paris,</hi> in mourning Gownes, each carrying before and behind him an Eſcutchion of the Dukes Armes, they made this Proclamation.</p>
               <p>All Nobles and devout perſons pray for the ſoul of the moſt excellent and moſt puiſſant Prince, <hi>Victor Amady</hi> by the grace of God Duke of <hi>Savoy, Chablais, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta,</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> Prince and perpetuall Vicar of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, Marqueſſe of <hi>Saleuceſſe, Nizze,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Dukes titles, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Romaut</hi> and <hi>Aſti, Banes,</hi> and <hi>Favoigni,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellei,</hi> of the Marqueſate of <hi>Seva,</hi> and <hi>Doviola</hi> late de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, for whoſe ſoul the King hath appointed Prayers and Service in the great Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> at which place, on Wedneſday next in the afternoon, ſhall be ſaid the Veſpers and Vigils for the dead, to continue untill ten of the clock upon Thurſday morning.</p>
               <p>Wedneſday the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8, the Courts and incorporated bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies aſſembled in the ſaid Church, the train band of the City having worke enough to make way for them through the preſſe of people, which was ſo great that the Church doores were forced to be kept ſhut for the ſpace of an houre, that time being ſpent to ſetch in the Kings order for thoſe Veſpers and Vigils, which were ſaid by the Deane, Chanter, and Canons in a dolefull tune agreeable to that mournfull action without ſound of Muſique in the Quire of the ſaid Cathedrall. The Quire was hung round with five ſeverall rowes of <note place="margin">The manner of the ſervice with all Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</note> black cloth, and two of Velvet, beſides the benches, ſeats, chairs, and pews, which were covered as the high Altar, and the ground ſpread with black cloth. The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:178347:42"/> of the Church was ſo great, that thouſands of men there would have ſeemed but a ſmall number, yet that <note place="margin">The firſt days ſervice.</note> was hung round with two rowes of black cloth, and one of Velvet to the great doore of the Church which was hanged double, as was that alſo which led to the Archbiſhops Palace by a pair of winding ſtaires which were covered with blacke, as were the two Halls of the Palace both prepared for the receit of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
               <p>This was the firſt days work, the next morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween eight and nine, the ſame aſſembly met to attend the three yong Princes of <hi>Nemours,</hi> the chief Mourners, who expected them in the Palace Hall, robed in black <note place="margin">The office for the ſecond day</note> Gowns with long trains each of ſix els apiece born up by the Gentlemen. The Maſter of the Ceremonies thence conducted them into the <hi>Quire,</hi> having three Heralds going before him attended with their King at Armes, before whom marched the 23 Cryers in the ſame habit as they had done the day before, and among them 100 poore men in mourning Gowns and Hoods, each carrying a lighted torch garniſhed with his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Highneſſe his Armes, and before all theſe the train band of the City, having work enough to keepe off the multitude, whoſe curioſity had drawne them thither in ſuch troups, that they peſtered the way, and hindred the Mourners, who were to attend the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and the Quire whither they came at laſt, and there abode four houres together. In a Gallery above them, were placed the Officers of the Chamber of Accompts, the Court of Aids, and the Corporation of the City. Oppoſite to them on the other ſide, ſtood the prime Preſident the Duke of <hi>Montbaſon,</hi> the Counſellours of the Court, and the Rector of the Vniverſity attended with eight Beadles with their ſilver Maces covered
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:178347:42"/> with Cypreſſe, which filled the lower end of the Quire. The Queen was ſeated where ſhe might ſee all and not be ſeen. <hi>Madamoſella</hi> and the princeſſe of <hi>Condy</hi> for their better conveniency were placed in the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's ſeat, he being then abſent. The Popes Ordinary <hi>Nuncio</hi> was ſeated on a bench at the ſide of the Altar, and the <hi>Venetian</hi> Embaſſadour by him, the Embaſſador of <hi>Savoy</hi> being not able to attend by reaſon of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition of his body, many Biſhops in their ordinary habits being ſeated on a bench at the great doore of the Quire, and the reſt of the ſpace filled with people of all conditions and ſexes.</p>
               <p>The Office was performed by <hi>Routhiller,</hi> coadjutor to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Tours,</hi> who with <hi>de la Barde</hi> a <note place="margin">With all the particular Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</note> Canon of the Cathedrall, which aſſiſted him in black Velvet Copes, garniſhed with the Armes of the decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Duke, celebrated Maſſe before the great Altar of the Quire, which was adorned with many white wax tapers burning and garniſhed with double Eſcutchions of <hi>Or</hi> and <hi>Argent.</hi> At the ſide of the ſaid Altar, a Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board was erected in forme of another Altar, garniſhed with foure great Candleſticks, one Croſſe, and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Veſſels required for that ſervice, all of ſilver en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven. The Archbiſhop officiating. <hi>Le Sieur des Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> Secretary to the Cardinall Duke, Chanter and Canon of the ſaid Church, and his Sub-chanter held a Quire by the ſide of the burning Chappell, which was of 1 a foot long and 10 wide, compoſed of nine pillars charged with double croſſe-bars, upon which were ſet 800 great Lights of yellow wax.</p>
               <p>Vnder the middle of the roofe was an Herſe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the body of the Duke, covered with cloth of gold, quartered by a Croſſe of white Sattin, adorned with foure great Scutcheons bearing the Armes of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:178347:43"/> deceaſed Duke, in a broydery of <hi>Or</hi> and <hi>Argent,</hi> and about it ſtood ſix great Candleſticks of ſilver gilt, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with great white waxe lights, and double Scut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chions of the ſame bearing. The foure Heralds of Arms were ſeated upon four low-ſtools, at the foure corners of the <hi>Capella Ardente,</hi> towards the head of the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative Herſe, betwixt the two chiefe Heralds ſtood an holy-water-pot of ſilver covered with blacke, and neer that were laid two cuſhions of black Velvet. At the feet of the Herſe towards the Altar betwixt the two laſt Heralds, there was an other leſſer Altar, and upon that foure Candleſticks, and a Croſſe of carved ſilver. Vpon the head of the Herſe, there ſtood a pillow of black Velvet, upon which was placed a Dukes Crown, covered with black Cypreſſe. The foure Seſſes, which made the towre of the <hi>Capella Ardente,</hi> were covered with cloth, and black Velvet, garniſhed with four great Scutcheons of the ſame bearing, woven with <hi>Or</hi> and <hi>Argent,</hi> the reſt being powdered with many other leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Armes. Beſides the other lights, the place deſigned for the Choriſters was hanged, with three rowes of cloth, and two of black Velvet; all which were gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with great lights, and double Scutcheons. About the Arches and Galleries of the body of the Church and Quire, 1200 great lights were blazing: So that in all, during the Service, which was performed with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent harmony of Muſique, by the Chaunters, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, and Choriſters, no leſſe then 3000 wax Tapers were ſeen burning. In the time of the Liturgy, the three yong Princes of <hi>Nemours,</hi> made their offering, and preſented each one, a white waxe Candle: the firſt offered one garniſhed with foure Scutcheons of <hi>Or,</hi> the ſecond of three, and the third of two, which were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them by the Maſter of the Ceremonies, for the ſame
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:178347:43"/> purpoſe. Then the <hi>Sieur</hi> of <hi>Liugendres,</hi> placed in the Chanters ſeat, made an Oration ſit for the time, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Princes honour, contayning a relation of his acts in his life and pious death.</p>
               <p>The Funerall Oration done, the ſervice was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued: after the elevation of the holy Sacrament, foure torches of white wax, were carried by four Mourners clothed in black without Hoods, &amp; in the end the three yong Lords, thanking the company, with an accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med reverence, their devotions being done upon their knees, when they had caſt ſome holy-water upon the Herſe, as did all the reſt of quality, depart each man to his own place.</p>
               <p>The Duke is dead,
<q>
                     <l>At non ille ferox qui ſe jactavit Iberus,</l>
                     <l>Nec ſcelerata manus Catilinae—</l>
                  </q> he neither fell immaturely by the hand of the <hi>Titans,</hi> the men of warre his Enemies, nor by clandeſtine trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of a <hi>Iaques Clement,</hi> or <hi>Ravilliack,</hi> the bloudy practices of murdrous Aſſaſſinates, but ſubmitted to Fate, ſickneſſe the Harbinger of death, prepared his way, and he traced it: two of his ſubjects <hi>Capuchins,</hi> of that order which in his life, he moſt reſpected, attended upon him in his death, the thred of their lives being cut off by the violence, and malice of ſome impious <hi>Jews,</hi> for profeſſing the Name of Chriſt, the Divine Power having ſo ordered it, that he would not want a cleer witneſſe againſt that obſtinate people, in the duskineſſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Chriſtian Religion. The ſtory is thus delivered from <hi>Lions, Chambery,</hi> and <hi>Roven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was dwelling at <hi>Carrieu</hi> in <hi>Piemont</hi> a <hi>Iew</hi> named <hi>Macohabe,</hi> aged above 60 yeers, and ſo weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:178347:44"/> that he maintained a Family of 12 Males, and nine Females, and in theſe late warres betwixt the Duke of of <hi>Savoy</hi> and the State of <hi>Millain,</hi> had furniſhed his Highneſſe with above 12000 Duckets. Hee had a Nephew called <hi>Iacob Rabby,</hi> who had ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence with the Chriſtians, which deſiring his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <note place="margin">Two <hi>Copuchins</hi> murdered by a <hi>Iew</hi> at <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riew.</hi>
                  </note> with much entreaty perſwaded him to hear a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon made by a <hi>Capuchin</hi> in Lent laſt at <hi>Carriew.</hi> The Argument of the Sermon was that Ieſus the Saviour of the world was already come into the world in humane fleſh, born of an immaculate Virgin by the operation of the Holy Ghoſt, and that there was no other Prophet to be longer expected in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> which being proved and explained by the Propheticall Scriptures, cauſed the young <hi>Jew</hi> to ſearch more narrowly into that my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, which had ſo long bin concealed from him, and (being aftewards confirmed in the truth by private conference) to renounce his Iudaiſme, and to deſire Baptiſme for his initiation into Chriſtianity. <hi>Maccabe</hi> his Vncle hearing of his converſion, ſwelled with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight and rage againſt the <hi>Capuchins,</hi> vowing to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged of that order, and as many Chriſtian ſoules, as he could meet withall conveniently. The forenamed Friars fell into his hands, and were made the Anvils of his malicious miſchief. By command from their ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, they were ſent upon a journey, and belated upon the way, met caſually with the old Wolviſh <hi>Iew,</hi> who forecaſting how to glut himſelf with their bloud, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly invites them to take a lodging at his houſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth a faire and kinde welcome, which they being wearied, and benighted did not refuſe, but they were no ſooner entred into the houſe of the perſidious <hi>Jew,</hi> but ſtraight the doores were made faſt, and they were environed with the whole Family, which entertained
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:178347:44"/> them with words of deſpight, calling them Apoſtataes, ſaying, that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> of the <hi>Iewes</hi> would come, and put the Chriſtians to confuſion, and adding horrid blaſphemies againſt our Saviour, bound the poor ſouls, hands, and feet, beat them with cudgels, threatning torment upon torment, unleſſe they would confeſſe the bleſſed Virgin to have bin a common proſtitute. It could not but grate the eares of any Chriſtian, to heare thoſe execrable words, the <hi>Capuchins</hi> would not have heard them ſpoken, much leſſe utter them, but comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting each other by mutuall encouragements, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receive their Martyrdome ſtill mayntaining the fundamentall point, and hing of ſalvation, till the <hi>Iews</hi> grown mad with rage at their conſtant reſolution firſt cut out their tongues, and then ſtabd them to death with knives in many parts of the body ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>(Michaey</hi> firſt, and <hi>Seraphino</hi> afterwards, and then carried them in their habits into a dark Vault, thinking to conceal this horrid murder.</p>
               <p>But the bloud of the Friers cried to Heaven, and that juſtice, which will not permit ſuch haynous ſins to go <note place="margin">The murder diſcovered.</note> unpuniſhed, made it known by the tongue of a <hi>Iewiſh</hi> childe, of eight or nine years of age, which playing with the Chriſtian children in the ſtreet the next morning, told how <hi>Macabe</hi> had aſſaſſinated two <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> &amp; hid their carcaſſes. The words of the child, cauſed this truth to be ſuſpected amongſt the inhabitants, who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Friers go into the <hi>Iews</hi> houſe, and not hearing of their return, came together, forced open his gates, ſearched for their bodies, and found them as the child had told, and therupon apprehended the whole Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the child only excepted, and the Actors by ſentence <note place="margin">The <hi>Iews</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and executed.</note> of the Senate at <hi>Turin</hi> were all burned alive, <hi>Octob.</hi> 2. 12, their goods conſiſcate, the one part to the uſe of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:178347:45"/> the Ducheſſe Regent, and the other to the child which revealed the murder, and turned Chriſtian, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>The Fabrick of the State of <hi>Italy</hi> did ſeeme to totter this laſt Summer, the great Biſhop was twice ſtruck <note place="margin">The Popes ſickneſſe and recovery.</note> with a palſie, and the Cardinall <hi>Barberino</hi> his Nephew, by his appointment governed as a Vice-pope during his weakneſſe, to the grievance of the whole Conclave, The Cardinall of <hi>Savoy</hi> Comprotector of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>de Medicis,</hi> ſuppoſing his ſickneſſe mortall, laboured to promote the Cardinall <hi>Sanſiſto</hi> to the Papacy, but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> recovered, was informed of each particular, which had hapned, aſſembled the Conclave created eleven new Cardinals, and yet liveth, <hi>Sanſiſto</hi> which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for his ſucceſſor being dead before him. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the Dukes <hi>de Mirandola,</hi> is quite extinguiſhed, their was but one leſt of that name, and he an illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, who having obtained by the interceſſion of his <note place="margin">The death of the Dukes of <hi>Mirandula</hi> and <hi>Mantua.</hi>
                  </note> Friends, the inveſtiture of that Duchy, is dead ſince without iſſue. The Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> hath yielded to Fate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:178347:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. The Actions and Occurrences in the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Arre, if once begun, ſpreadeth like a Canker. A Prince, engaged in armes, hath commonly a troubled State, and reſtleſſe head, his Enemy waits all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, and unleſſe providence guide him, hee can finde ſecurity no where. The Cardinall Infant ſtood like a common bounder between two Enemies: the <hi>French</hi> upon the South and Eaſt of the Provinces under his care, made an invaſion upon him: the Vnited States upon the North did the like, and now to fortiſie himſelf, firſt, he cauſed the City of <hi>Hulſt</hi> to double their Paliſadoes, and renew their Fortifications, and then the Garriſons of <hi>Mech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, Lyre, Breda,</hi> and the other places in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Brabant,</hi> where his old ſouldiers were wintered, he drew out ſuch Forces and Amunition, as was thought
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:178347:46"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:178347:46"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:178347:47"/> fit to withſtand them. The beginning of <hi>Iune,</hi> the Princes Rendevouz was appointed, 80 Boates were <note place="margin">The States proparation for warre.</note> ſent from <hi>Bergenapzohm</hi> to <hi>Ramekens,</hi> the Enginers were ſent to <hi>Nimminghem,</hi> the <hi>Frizelanders</hi> met at <hi>Emerick,</hi> the Cardinall Infant fortifying in the interim <hi>Stivenſworth, Gennep,</hi> and other places, and ſending the Avantguard of his Horſe from <hi>Antwerp</hi> towards <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Highneſſe the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> kept his deſigne ſecret, ſome thought it had bin for <hi>Brugez,</hi> others for <hi>Hulſt,</hi> but none imagined, nor could tell certainly whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they tended. About the end of <hi>Iune,</hi> his Forces met together, were ſhipped at <hi>Gorcum,</hi> and though the winde blew hard, and cauſed ſome tempeſt, arrived <hi>Iuly</hi> the ſeventh new ſtile at the Keel. Free Camp was then publiſhed about the <hi>Rhine,</hi> all Excizes taken off, the Army then aſſembling together to attend his Highnes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Breda</hi> beſieged</note> pleaſure. Some time he ſtaid upon the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lack</hi> before <hi>Ramekens,</hi> and till the 19 of <hi>Iuly,</hi> no man had any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular knowledge of his meaning: then it was firſt diſcovered to Prince <hi>Henry Caſſimere</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> who with the Vantguard of his Army, led on towards <hi>Breda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The name of the Town is dignified with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a Baronry, is ſituate in the Country of <hi>Kempen,</hi> which is on part of the Province of <hi>Brabant,</hi> between <note place="margin">The deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Towne.</note> 
                  <hi>Lyre, Antwerp, Bergenapzohm, Tourn-hoult, Hogſtraten, Stievenbergen,</hi> and <hi>Gertrudenberg:</hi> ſeven leagues from each of the two firſt places, five from the third, foure from the fourth, three from the fifth, and two from the laſt, and hath under it ſeventeene Villages, beſides the Towns of <hi>Stiven-berg, Roſendendall,</hi> and <hi>Oſterhoult.</hi> It was the ordinary reſidence of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the houſe of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> to whom it fell in the yeer
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:178347:47"/> 1404, by the inter-marriage of <hi>Englebert,</hi> a Prince of that Family, with <hi>Iane</hi> the Inheritrix of that Territory. <note place="margin">Its condition under ſeverall Princes.</note> The Princes of that Race held it peaceably, till the yeer 1567, at which time <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> to leave it, till the yeer 1577; at which time he was newly poſſeſſed of it, and kept it four yeers, till that <hi>Iune</hi> 15/25, 1585, when driven out by violence, he again left it to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who kept it till the fourth of <hi>March</hi> 1590, at which time Captain <hi>Heranger</hi> ſurprized it by a Turf-boat which covered ſome force of men underneath: <hi>Grobendonk</hi> in the yeer 1599, laboured to ſurprize it, but failed, yet the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> took it by Famine in the yeer 1625, <hi>Iuly</hi> the fifth new ſtile, after a ſiege of ten moneths &amp; 22 days, ſince which time the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have kept it with a ſtrong Garriſon, which troubling the whole ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning Territory, and hindring all trade by the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Rivers, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> now reſolved to beſiege it. This was the motive which impelled him to this Enterprize, for proſequution wherof, he uſed this method.</p>
               <p>The Prince <hi>Henry Caſſimere</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> was ſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with the Vantguard of his Army, conſiſting of 44 Cornets of horſe, and 80 Companies of Foot to begirt it round, which hee did <hi>Iuly</hi> 13/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, driving away all the cattell that fed in the medows neer it, his Highneſſe in perſon the next day, comming before the Towne with <note place="margin">The Avant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard under Prince <hi>Henry Caſſimire</hi> blocks it up.</note> the body of his Army conſiſting of 40 Cornets of horſe more, and 230 Companies of Foot, and above 100 pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of canon, having before given order for 8 ſhips men of warre to guard the Chanell from <hi>Gertrudenberg</hi> to <hi>Stieven-bergen,</hi> that he might have a ſure paſſage to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall his Army by that River, he began with prayers, and cauſed ſupplication to be made through all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:178347:48"/> of the Vnited States for an happy happy iſſue of that deſigne. Their devotions once over, he fell to work, drew out the lines of his trenches, following the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> his plot-forme, imployed 8000 Boores in the work, and appointed their quarters to the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, <note place="margin">The works begun.</note> taking his own at <hi>Ginniken,</hi> aſſigning the Count <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> to the Village of the <hi>Hague,</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Morgan</hi> to lie upon the way towards <hi>Autwerpe,</hi> betwixt his owne quarter and the Count <hi>Williams,</hi> Count <hi>Henry Caſſimere</hi> Governour of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rieſland,</hi> being enquartered at the <hi>Heyde,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Bovillon</hi> at <hi>Tetringen</hi> and <hi>Heuſenheut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cardinall by this had notice of what the Prince intended, and loth to loſe ſo fair a Gem as <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> with an Army of 14000 Foot, and 6000 Horſe, many peeces of Ordnance, and good ſtore of Amuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, marched from <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> and came to <hi>Hogstraten,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Cardinal Infant ſeeks to relieve it.</note> thinking to impeach the Prince, and raiſe his ſiege be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was well ſet down: but to adventure to a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail, had bin to have put all to the Fortune of one day, he would not do it deſperatly, though hee had conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to aſſault him couragiouſly, therfore he ſent before him a Vant Currier <hi>Iohn de Naſſaw</hi> an experienced ſouldier with ninety Companies of Horſe to view the poſture of the Princes Army, and to acquaint him with the particulars. Hee found the Prince neither ſupinely ſleeping, nor in a looſe poſiture, as if there had bin no cauſe of feare expecting him: He knew the Cardinall to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn de Naſſaw</hi> ſent to deſcry, the Princes poſture.</note> he a man trained up from his youth in military Feats, &amp; ſtood in a firme Battalia to attend him. The Cardinall would not hazard all at once, but upon a good ground and informed of the Princes ſtrength and vigilancy, made no attempt upon the Campe, but retired toward the <hi>Hemeriſh-werth,</hi> and the <hi>Prince-land,</hi> leaving the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:178347:48"/> iſſue of the ſiege to the care of the preſidiary ſouldiers. The garriſon incloſed within their walles, and the <note place="margin">And finding the P. upon his guard, the C. departeth.</note> Princes Army, ſhewed their courage by many ſallyes, to get their liberty: but his Highneſſe his power orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his care, ſo farre availed him, that ſtill he repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them with loſſe, and in the end, entrenched him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo ſtrongly, cutting the <hi>Merk-dike</hi> to environ his trenches, that he neither feared the invaſion of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> campe without, nor the fallies of the garriſon from within.</p>
               <p>Count <hi>Henry,</hi> Governour of <hi>Vrieſ-land,</hi> by too much confidence was endangered, while the Pioners <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Henry Caſſimire</hi> neer to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed.</note> were labouring in the works. He went abroad to view the fortifications of the City, and at an old ruined houſe, where he feared no perill, was in hazard of his life or liberty: ſome of the garriſon were lurking in the Cellar, and leaping out ſuddenly, took hold of his bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and had ſurpriſed him ſuddenly, had not his horſe trained up to bounds and curvets) regained his liberty by ſtrength.</p>
               <p>It would be long to proceed to each particular. <hi>Iuly</hi> 23. old ſtile, the garriſon made another ſally, and for a time became maſters of an halfe Moone, but were bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out immediately, and on Thurſday following, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 3. of the clock in the morning, 1400 men of them <note place="margin">The garriſon ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lly out upon the Campe.</note> aſſaulted againe the ſame halfe Moone, ſeized on it, and held it for an houre, at which time they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed, with the loſſe of ſive Captains, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther officers and ſouldiers: the aſſiegeants themſelves not repoſſeſſing the place, without the death of many men in <hi>Bredrods</hi> quarter, with one Lieutenant, and 5 or 6 ſouldiers of <hi>Mauritius</hi> his company.</p>
               <p>The Camp made its excurſions abroad, as well as the garriſon made its ſallies upon the Army. The Prince by his labour and providence, had taken ſuch order,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:178347:49"/> that they could not breake forth ſo frequently out of their encloſure. He having already raiſed two batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <note place="margin">The Princes order to keepe the Garriſon in.</note> one neare the <hi>Ginniken</hi> Water-mill, about 600 pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the City, and the other in Count <hi>Williams</hi> Quarter, kept by two <hi>corps de guard,</hi> and ſecured by two Redouts to prevent their eruption. The way into the field was open for the garriſon, and <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 6. new ſtile, young <hi>Monſieur de Mee,</hi> went abroad upon the Heath with 70 Cavaliers, and there encountred with 80 wagons loaden with Wine, <hi>Aqua vita,</hi> and Beere, deſigned for the Infanta's campe, ſurprized the Convoy, broke the veſſels in pieces, and brought to the camp 70 juſty horſes, which were ſould by ſound of the drum the day following.</p>
               <p>The hearts of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſouldiers in the Cardinals Army by this, began to faile them. A whole troope of <hi>Burgundians</hi> ran away together, and among them one <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, who joyntly affirmed, that if they were not kept in by the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> horſe, more would follow them. Yet though his men began to decline him, the Cardinall Infant would not forſake himſelfe; but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the improbability he had to relieve the City, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected how to advance the affaires of the Catholike <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enloo</hi> taken by the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Infanta. A Baſtard.</note> King elſewhere, and marched towards <hi>Venloo</hi> and <hi>Ruremond,</hi> end took in <hi>Venloo</hi> in the ſpace of 5 dayes, (though it was garriſon'd with 1100 able men) by the cowardiſe, trechery, and wantonneſſe of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. One of the family of <hi>Bredrode,</hi> who enticed (as is reported) by the ſeducing face of a falſe Nun, with whom it was thought he had too familiar an acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, delivered up the keyes to the Infanta, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded him with the wages of his perfidiouſneſſe, a ſmall ſumme of money, with the which he went to <hi>Collen,</hi> to be ſecured from a juſt vengeance of the States, which though they could not apprehend his
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:178347:49"/> perſon, and put him to an actuall torture, executed him in <hi>eſſigie.</hi> Thence he advanced to <hi>Ruremond,</hi> which he <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruremond</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred upon compoſition.</note> thought to have ſurpriſed as ſpeedily, but the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour there, in his loyalty to the State, maintained it as long as he was able, though in the end he was forced to yeeld upon compoſition.</p>
               <p>It had been vain to have ſtaied in that quarter longer, little hope was there to advance his conqueſt further, the States, warned by the loſſe of theſe two laſt places, had double garriſon'd all the townes, and it was more probability, that by his ſtay, he might there conſume himſelfe and his Army, than enlarge his victories. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he had other irons in the ſire elſewhere. The <hi>French</hi> began to domineere in <hi>Henault</hi> and <hi>Artois,</hi> and had they found no oppoſition, they had invaded <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> the glory of thoſe Provinces under the <hi>Spaniard;</hi> and to make head againſt them. He was forced to leave the <hi>Maze,</hi> and march to the frontiers of <hi>Picardy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The hope of the garriſon in <hi>Breda,</hi> depended upon his ſuccours, and though they could not be ignorant that he was gone, and had left them, they were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, but uſed all their policy and might to weary out the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and force him to riſe, ſeeing they could not vanquiſh him. <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. the beſieged ſallied out againe, and fought ſo earneſtly, that as if their liberty were above their lives; they gave not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver combat till the horrid face of death appeared in the mangled bodies of ſome of their copartners, and of the aſſailants; then they retired, begd ceſſation of Armes for two houres, and obtained it for the buriall of their dead; and that work of piety being done, the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the few minutes was ſpent in friendly drinkings betwixt the garriſon and the camp; the preſidiaries ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſing to them in their owne liquor, and the camp an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering them in the Beere of <hi>Dort</hi> and <hi>Rotterdam,</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:178347:50"/> with which it was furniſhed. The ſands that meaſured out the time, were no ſooner runne, but both ſides fell againe to their acts of hoſtility, the Prince ſtill procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to make his approches neerer, although they were already brought within a ſtones caſt of the walles. In time he perfected what he had in his minde forecaſt, though not without coſt and expence both of bloud and money. <hi>Auguſt</hi> 23. old ſtile, he began to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the enemies Horn-work, and that day our Noble Countryman, (whoſe valour not appearing in bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes, but in fruits in his youth) the yong Colonell <hi>Goring,</hi> who commanded in the approches, and had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured too far into the then not fully fortified Shrub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gallery, received a faulcon-ſhot in his ancle, which to the eye of the Chirurgeons, appeared ſo dangerous, that they concluded, he could not eſcape unleſſe his legge were cut off: the Noble Gentleman bore the hurt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, but not the concluſion of his Chyrurgeous, he reſolved rather to loſe his life, then his limb, till per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by the divine adviſe of his Chaplaine, Doctor <hi>Calfe,</hi> he began to aſſent to the courſe preſcribed him. It was not without an argument of the divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that he ſhould thus demurre upon the manner of his cure; while they were thus perſwading him, and the Chyrurgeons preparing to diſmember him, an old ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Chyrurgeon commeth in, undertaketh the cure, and performed it happily, it being now ſcarce a blemiſh to the eye, and diſcernable onely by a little halting.</p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>Charnaſſe,</hi> Embaſſadour for the Chriſtian King to the States, and Generall of the <hi>French</hi> forces in that ſervice, ſped not that day ſo happily: He not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two dayes before, had received a ſhot upon his hat-band, which ſlipt away and did him no harme, but this day was ſtrucke more unfortunately upon the forehead, ſo loſing his life, to the great griefe of the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:178347:50"/> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who had often uſed his counſell both in his publique and private affaires.</p>
               <p>But the fate of the City now drew on, the Mines were ready, the galleries prepared, and the City brought to extremity, the Governour and garriſon ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulated upon theſe conditions.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Tbe Articles follow, as they are delivered ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly and plainely by the <hi>French.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item n="1">FIrſt, the Governour of <hi>Breda,</hi> with all the officers of warre, of what condition or quality ſoever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, even thoſe alſo who have formerly left the ſervice of the States, and now taken pay under the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſhall have liberty to depart from the towne without any ſtoppe or impeachment, with Armes and baggage, the Drum beating, Enſignes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaied, bullet in mouth, and match in cocke, in the rank and forme they uſed to obſerve when they marched in battalia, with a ſafe conduct for their lives and goods to <hi>Malines.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="2">2. They ſhall have licenſe to carry with them foure Pieces of Ordnance, &amp; two Morterers, ſuch as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour ſhall chooſe, with all their attirall, equipage, and ſhot and powder ſufficient for three diſcharges of each of them.</item>
                  <item n="3">3. They ſhall be furniſhed with horſe, waggons, and drivers, to carry that Artillery, thoſe Morterers, the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirall, and ammunition to <hi>Malines.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="4">4. All the other ammunition of warre, and proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of victuals appertaining to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſhall without ſtand be delivered to him whom his Highneſſe the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ſhall appoint to receive it, except
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:178347:51"/> ſuch victuals which ſhal be found ſould <hi>bonafide,</hi> before the 6 of this moneth new ſtile, when this treaty began, the ſale whereof ſhall ſtand good, and no man ſhall be ſearched, nor enquired after for buying it.</item>
                  <item n="5">5 All the Officers and Souldiers, ſicke and wounded, lying at the Hoſpitall, or elſewhere, ſhall be permitted to abide there, till they have recovered ſtrength to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, at which time there ſhall be given them a ſafe conduct, and accommodation to tranſport their Armes and baggage to the fore-named place <hi>Malines.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="6">6 The ſaid Governour ſhall be furniſhed with ſuch number of waggons and horſe as ſhall be requiſite, as well for the tranſportation of his own luggage and baggage, as of all the Officers and ſouldiers to <hi>Malines:</hi> under which names of luggage and baggage, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed all the Armes of the ſouldiers of the ſaid towne of <hi>Breda,</hi> even thoſe that be abſent, dead, ſick, wounded or ſled, nor ſhall thoſe waggons be ſearched by any man upon any pretence.</item>
                  <item n="7">7 Such as will have their luggage and baggage carried to <hi>Malines</hi> by water, ſhall be freely provided of boats to conduct them through <hi>Holland,</hi> which ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted and diſcharged of all impoſts, taxes, and pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoever, and for the ſafeguard of that lug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage and baggage, there ſhall be a competent number of men to conduct them, and thoſe boats ſhall not be ſearched nor arreſted by the way upon any pretext whatſoever, nor ſhall they unload any parcell untill they arive at <hi>Malines.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="8">8 The Governour, Captains, Officers, military Iudges, and others, receiving pay of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> both Eccleſiaſticks and Lay-men, as alſo the widowes and children, which have in the ſaid towne of <hi>Breda,</hi> any houſes or inheritances, whether they be upon the States of <hi>Brabant</hi> in that juriſdiction, or in the town,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:178347:51"/> whether land or moveable goods, ſhall have the ſpace and terme of two yeeres of this treaty, to tranſport, ſell, engage, or otherwiſe diſpoſe of the ſaid goods, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſaid terme, ſhall enjoy the ſaid Rents, Farmes with the Houſes, Fruits, and goods already gotten, or to be gotten in that ſpace, be they of what nature or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſoever they may be.</item>
                  <item n="9">9. The Officers and ſouldiers of all conditions, may leave their wives and children in the towne during the ſaid terme of two yeers, to diſpoſe of their goods move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and immoveable, whether they be in the ſaid town or elſewhere, without danger of ſeiſure or confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
                  <item n="10">10. No Officer or other ſouldier, neither now, nor hereafter ſhall be arreſted for the rents of the houſes they have poſſeſt, nor have their baggage ſearched to make payment of any debt, be they either ſuch as ſhall depart preſently with the Garriſon, or ſuch as being ſick or wounded, cannot depart till they be recovered.</item>
                  <item n="11">11. All the ſouldiers, priſoners on both ſides, of what rank ſoever ſhall be ſet at liberty without ranſome, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only for their victuals, according to the taxe of the Quarter. The ſervants and other priſoners ſhall depart alſo paying the charges of their expenſes.</item>
                  <item n="12">12 The booty that hath been gotten by thoſe of the town, both before and during the ſiege, ſhall not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them back again.</item>
                  <item n="13">13 After the Articles of this compoſition are ſealed, the Governour of <hi>Breda</hi> ſhall have time given him to ſend an expreſſe to the Cardinall Infant with a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy to acquaint him with what hath paſſed, all which the Governour may doe the ſame day this Treaty ſhall be ſigned.</item>
                  <item n="14">14. The conditions forenamed being confirmed,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:178347:52"/> two dayes ſhall bee granted to the Governour and his Souldiers to prepare for their departure, which time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expired, the ſaid Governour, and the ſaid Officers of the Garriſon ſhall promiſe to depart (to wit) upon Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday next being the tenth of <hi>October,</hi> new ſtile, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the morning.</item>
                  <item n="15">15. It is intended that till the two days be paſt, that no perſon of the town ſhall come into the Campe, nor any of the army ſhall enter into the town, but that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſhall contain himſelf, during this time, in their trenches and fortifications, without doing any act or hoſtilitie, for aſſurance wherof, there ſhall be hoſtages interchangeably given on both ſides, this article being reſolved of, to avoid all diſorder which might happen other wayes.</item>
                  <item n="16">16. Before that the Garriſon departeth, there ſhall be given two ſufficient hoſtages by the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> which ſhall march with the ſaid Garriſon, their armes and baggage to <hi>Malines,</hi> and in exchange of them two other hoſtages ſhall be given by the Governour, which ſhall abide with his Excellencie, till the ſaid hoſtages and waggons be returned, at which time his Excellency ſhall ſend the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> hoſtages with a ſafe conduct to <hi>Malines.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="17">17 The Officers, Captains, and others comprized in the firſt Article of this preſent treaty, having any armes, Barks, or Shallops, or other utenſils of warre, may either ſell them or tranſport them, neither ſhall ſuch as are tranſported, bought or ſold be ſearched upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</item>
                  <item n="18">18 There ſhall no reſtitution be made of Horſes, armes, Merchants ware, or other baggage held for law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full booty, and ſold, nor ſhall any particular man be ſearched.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:178347:52"/>
               <p> Dated at the Camp before <hi>Breda,</hi> the ſeventh of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> new ſtile, 1637.</p>
               <p>Theſe Articles concerned the Garriſon in particular, which came not to treat till our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Souldiers had taken by aſſault a <hi>Ravelin</hi> in the Mote, and the <hi>French</hi> an halfe Moon before the <hi>Gininkens</hi> Port: at which time, the mine being ready to play, and 5000 Souldiers of divers Nations, but of one heart, in armour of proofe, provided with Inſtruments for ſuch an occaſion expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the iſſue prepared for the aſſault: at which time they firſt hung out a white flag upon their walls, as a token that they deſired to capitulate, and afterwards ſend out two Captaines to conferre with the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> about the heads of the treaty, he ſending two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the army into the City. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captaines, one by Nation a <hi>Burgundian,</hi> the other a <hi>Freeſlander,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the Prince <hi>Octob.</hi> the ſixth new ſtile, and upon the overture of their conference, returned into the City, from whence about five in the Evening, eight men of note and authority among the people came to his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie's Gampe, to conclude the forenamed Articles, <hi>(viz.)</hi> two men of authority among the Clergy; the chief judge, and the Preſident of the town, two Burgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, and the two Sheriffs. Theſe perſonages of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thus contracted for <hi>Gomar Fourdin</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the Garriſon, which accepted the concluſion, and <hi>Oct.</hi> 10 new ſtile, marched thence about 11 a clock, being in all about 1585 men Muſquetiers, and <hi>Coſtlets, Almans, Burgundians, Spaniards, Walloons,</hi> and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, armed with 48 Enſigues, and four or 500 ſervants imployed about the baggage, having in the middle of their troops about 7 or 800 waggons, ſix pieces of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non (the courteſie of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> giving them
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:178347:53"/> two more than what they covenanted for, two Morte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, 12 tuns of powder with other amunition, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour followed in his Caroach by reaſon of the indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of his body, with two Officers and ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallary, being come out of the town, mounted an horſe, and went to ſalute the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who expected him in a place where foure wayes met, accompanied with <hi>Charles Lodovick,</hi> the Prince Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> Duke <hi>Robert</hi> the Elector's brother, the yong Prince his own ſonne, the Counts <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Henry Caſſimere,</hi> and other Lords, and the Complement ended, went on toward <hi>Malines,</hi> where this ſtory muſt leave him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. The Marine Occurrences.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He dry Land was not the only ſtage of action,
<q>
                     <l>—vidit in undis</l>
                     <l>Et Thetys ignotas &amp; Galathea feras.</l>
                  </q> The Military Fleets of divers Kingdoms, ſome imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely to ſecure the coaſts, others for tranſportation of Souldiers, others for invaſion, and the ſhipping for trade, plowing the face of the Mayn, made the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean ſeeme to carry ſo many moving Iſlands, that part appearing like a woodland where the Navies lay wind-bound, or rode at anchor, yet diſcovering it ſelfe again to be Sea, when the ſails were hoyſed, and the veſſels left that ſtation.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Archipelago</hi> was furrowed by the Pirats of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerte, Algier,</hi> and <hi>Tunis (Sally</hi> being then blocked up, by our worthy and vallant Countriman, Captaine <hi>Rauiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borow)</hi> which ſought for pillage upon the Chriſtians ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:178347:53"/> by Sea, or upon the <hi>European</hi> ſhoare: by the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of <hi>Malta,</hi> which endevoured to make prize of thoſe Renegadoes, and the Navies of the Chriſtian and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Kings, each of them intending to preſerve his own, and endamage the others territories.</p>
               <p>The Navy of <hi>Spaine</hi> had changed its Generall <hi>(Don Melchior Borgia,</hi> being aſſigned in the roome of the Duke of <hi>Ferrandina)</hi> but not the former deſigne. The Dominions of the Chriſtian King were the maine ſcope of its hoſtility, and thitherwards 21 Gallies well armed and mann'd with above 3000 ſouldiers, rowed by the <note place="margin">The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> deſigne upon the Rode of St <hi>Tropez</hi> and <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheau</hi> failing.</note> way of <hi>Sardinia,</hi> and were diſcovered by the <hi>French</hi> in the Gulph of Saint <hi>Tropez</hi> upon the Coaſt of <hi>Provence, June,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The project muſt needs have took had it not bin prevented by much circumſpection, <hi>Mont Guion,</hi> who commanded the <hi>French</hi> Garriſon in the town and Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadell, under the Marſhall <hi>de Vitry,</hi> at their firſt approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prepared to hinder their landing, but their haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting his, and ſome of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Souldiers landed at <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> with a purpoſe to ſurround the Cittadell, hee ſallied forthwith 120 Souldiers of the Garriſon, and charged the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Vantguard ſo couragiouſly, that hee beat them back to their Boats, and enforced them to ſeek for the ſafeguard of their lives in the Sea, whither their precipitious confuſed haſt carried them. It was fortune that crowned his action. His ſmall Forces conſiſting of Landmen, could not have maintained that Port-towne againſt ſuch an Armado: By good hap there was in the Harbour at the ſame time four veſſels of the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, <hi>(viz)</hi> two Pinnaces named the Royall, and the Cardinall and two Frigots, which kept the mouth of the Harbour, and by their frequent Cannonadoes aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the Cittadell, played upon the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet ſo ſucceſſefully with 300 vollies of ſhot, that they forced the Enemy to retire out of the Gulfe, and defeated him of his project.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:178347:54"/>
               <p> Yet the Seene only was altered, and not the <hi>Spaniards</hi> purpoſe, The Port of St. <hi>Rapheau</hi> did preſent It ſelfe to the fancy of the invaders, who failing of their end at St. <hi>Tropez</hi> tugged thither intending to ſurprize it, before it could be well provided for defence. The Marſhall <hi>de Vitry</hi> was the firſt, but not the only Diſcoverer of that enterprize, conceal it he could not, it being apparantly known to all the inhabitants about <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> (where hee then reſided) the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gallies rowing before the eyes of the people. The Count of <hi>Harcourt,</hi> Generall of the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, the ſame day that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Navy went from St. <hi>Tropez,</hi> departed from <hi>Treius,</hi> where hee had been entertained at Supper, by the Marſhall <hi>de Vitry</hi> the night before, and had not failed above one hour and an half, but that he kenn'd the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gallies, and obſerved with what eagerneſſe the ſlaves imployed their ſinews, to bring them up to ſome of the Sea-townes, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently made to land, muſtered up the Forces of the Country, which comming in continually, beat off the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armado from the Port of S. <hi>Rapheau;</hi> when they had burnt one <hi>French</hi> Bark only, their intention being to have done the like to all the ſhips which lay at anchor in that rode.</p>
               <p>From St. <hi>Rapheau,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Navy retired into the Bay, where being informed that ten ſhips of <hi>Holland</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Sp. Fleet ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſeth ten <hi>Holland</hi> ſhips bound for <hi>Genoa.</hi>
                  </note> were bound for <hi>Genoa,</hi> with Corn and Spicery, &amp; other Merchandize amounting to the value of three Millions of Crowns, the Flees way layed them, and in a calme after two days fight, having ſunke the <hi>Dutch</hi> Admirall, took the other nine, two wherof they conducted to <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> and the other ſeven to <hi>Morguez,</hi> where they ſold the goods as a vile and unproportionable value. The ſtate of <hi>Genoa,</hi> to which theſe goods were conſigned, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured much for their reſtitution, and ſent one Agent to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Admirall, and another to the Governour of <hi>Millain</hi> to require it, and that being denied, it cauſed
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:178347:54"/> ſome heart-burning betwixt the <hi>Genoveſes</hi> and the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> in <hi>Italy, Den Melchior Borgia</hi> deſiring liberty that his Fleet might come and refreſh it ſelfe in ſome of the Harbours of that State, and the Magiſtrate abſolutely refuſing to grant it, upon pretence that they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by the Merchants lately taken from the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and not only ſo by his owne word proteſting the reſentment of that ſeeming injuſtice, but by the deeds of the peaſants about <hi>Araſſe,</hi> breaking out with violence upon the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mariners, when they came to water upon their Coaſt, ſlaying ſome, chaſing the reſt, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king from them 170 barrels of freſh water, of which the Navy ſtood in need, pretending that they found them robbing of their Olive-yards. It is no point of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <note place="margin">The <hi>Genoeſes</hi> ſeek to have them reſtored, but prevail not.</note> to provoke a potent enemy. That politike State of <hi>Genoa,</hi> however diſpleaſed with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, did not deſiſt from promotion of their cauſe for one deniall, nor yet breake out into open enmity. Again they diſpatched <hi>Signior Luca Spinola</hi> to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and the <hi>Signiors Chiavari</hi> and <hi>Someliui</hi> to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of <hi>Spaine</hi> reſident in that City, about the ſame negotiation, who again denying to make any reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and juſtifying their detention of the goods, becauſe they were taken out of <hi>Holland</hi> Bottomes, and upon the <hi>French</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, both thoſe States being enemies to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike King, they diſpatched another Advocate to the Viceroy of <hi>Naples</hi> to intermediate betwixt the State &amp; the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generall, and he refuſing to meddle out of his own Sphere, as laſt they ſent an Embaſſador to the Catholike King, whoſe anſwer is yet expected.</p>
               <p>Here was the period of the actions of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy in the <hi>Archipelago.</hi> A ſtorm was riſen in the new We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern world, and had ſo ſhattered the frame of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The arrivall of Count <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice</hi> at <hi>Pharnam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buck.</hi>
                  </note> State there, that is required both men &amp; mony to repair it. To this purpoſe, <hi>Don Antonio de Ocquendo,</hi> was ſent from <hi>Major<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a,</hi> with one Gally to make choice of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:178347:55"/> beſt ſhips in the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Fleet, and to tranſport them to <hi>Braſil</hi> againſt the Forces of the Vnited <hi>Netherlander</hi> States there, whoſe fortunate progreſſe had dilated and inlarged the States Dominions there. His Excellency the Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> to whom the States had given a pleny-potentiary Commiſſion for the ordering of their affairs there, arrived at <hi>Pharnamboucg, Ianuary</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, where being entertained with the joyfull acclamations of the <hi>Dutch</hi> plantations, after ſome dayes ſpent in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving &amp; receiving of entertainment, the end of his voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age <note place="margin">And his victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at <hi>Porto Calvo.</hi>
                  </note> not being complement but action, <hi>Ian.</hi> 26. <hi>Febr</hi> 5. hee ſent before him the Admirall <hi>Lichthart</hi> to <hi>Serenhim,</hi> where his army lay on ſhipboard, himſelfe following by land with one company of horſe and certaine fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks. His deſigne was againſt the Fort of <hi>Provocation,</hi> &amp; <hi>Porto Calvo,</hi> where the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generall the <hi>Count de Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niola</hi> lay with an army of 4000 me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his name was grown terrible to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> army: the <hi>Gount</hi> would not abide his comming, but though fortified with four Redouts, having garriſoned the Fort with 600 men, fled by the way of <hi>Alegoa.</hi> News of his flight was brought to the <hi>Count of Naſſaw,</hi> who inſtantly begirting the Fort with one part of his Forces, diſpatched the <hi>Colonell Manifield</hi> to purſue the <hi>Spaniſh Count,</hi> who overtook his Rereward, and ſlue about 200 of his men, and then returned to the Campe. <hi>Count Maurice</hi> all this while was buſied in making his approches, raiſing of foure batteries, and ordering of things required for the ſiege, which he followed ſo earneſtly, that by the end of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> new ſtile, hee forced the Garriſon to capitulate for want of freſh water, their conditions being, that they ſhould march away the third of <hi>March</hi> new ſtile, with high and low weapons, one peece of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and be tranſported to <hi>Hispaniola</hi> or <hi>Saint Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minga.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:178347:55"/>
               <p> The victory was of conſequence, both in regard of the ſtrength of the place, and the wealth therein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; it was the ſtrongeſt Fort the enemy had in that territory, ordained for their Magazine, yeelded the Conqueror 22 Pieces of braſſe Ordnance, 5 iron Pieces, 4 Copper Morterers, 800 great Granadoes, 2000 hand-granadoes, 46395 pounds of powder, 6034 pounds of match, 9750 pounds of lead, opened the way to <hi>Todos los Santos,</hi> whither the <hi>Dutch</hi> Generall preſently ſent his Army, was taken with the loſſe of ſixe common men, and two prime Officers, the Lord <hi>Carlo,</hi> baſe ſonne to the late Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Dunkarcke</hi> a valiant ſouldier, who was ſlaine with a great ſhot from the Fort in time of the ſiege: and this rich atchievement, purchaſed ſo eaſily, could not but cauſe a generall thankſgiving, and triumphs of joy among the <hi>Dutch</hi> plantations, which being cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated upon <hi>March</hi> the 8 new ſtile at <hi>Pharnam, boucg,</hi> where after Sermon, 4 Companies of Citizens, and one of Souldiers preſenting themſelves in their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, victory was proclaimed by the roaring throats of althe Canons about the town; firſt of thoſe in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dout of <hi>Bruin,</hi> the next, of thoſe in the Sconce of <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</hi> the Land-Caſtle, and the Water-Caſtle, and the ſhips then in harbour, and laſtly by thoſe of the Stone-Redout, the Fort five-hook and the ſconce <hi>Emilia,</hi> the Citizens and Souldiers concluding the triumph with their Muſquetadoes, joying that by this meanes they enjoyed the 4 North Provinces of <hi>Braſil</hi> in peace, and had extended their dominions to the length of 400 <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles, the <hi>Portugals</hi> comming in voluntarily, and offering their fealty to the States of the united Provinces.</p>
               <p>The Gallyes of <hi>Byſerte</hi> made an invaſion upon the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> and ſurpriſed there 4 great Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots armed and loaden with corne, and other merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes appertaining to the Prince of <hi>Cariati,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartned with this ſpoyle, purſued the Signior <hi>Giovan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:178347:56"/> 
                  <hi>Baptiſta Laſagna</hi> a Genueſſe appointed Governour of <hi>Corſica,</hi> by the State of <hi>Genoa,</hi> as he was going to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <note place="margin">The Gallies of <hi>Byſerte</hi> pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage the Sea towns in the Kingdome of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </note> his dignity. Yet him they miſt; he was neer up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gorne</hi> when they firſt diſcovered him, and he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving againe what they aymed at, made haſte thither, and ſaved both his ſhip and perſon: the Gallies of <hi>Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cany</hi> putting to ſea preſently, to ſurpriſe the bold Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians, whoſe number and ſtrength exceeding the <hi>Florentines,</hi> the Pyrats having a fleet of 16 Gallies, and the great Dukes ſubjects but of 6. the <hi>Tuſcanes</hi> were faine to retreat to the Port of <hi>Calvi</hi> for their owne ſecurity.</p>
               <p>It was then a time of terrour to all the townes of the Sea coaſt in the Kingdome of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Calabria.</hi> The <note place="margin">The Viceroy of <hi>Naples</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides to ſecure them.</note> Viceroy was enforced to exact ſtrange contributions for the maintenance of thoſe places. The Nobility di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſted his courſe, and would have ſent to the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> to have acquainted him with their oppreſſions; the Commons complained of the heavy burthen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended their diſability to beare it, their ſtates being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready much impoveriſhed by the late warres, yet the wiſe Viceroy ſo behaved himſelfe, that by his owne private negotiations with the Nobility, and the publiks exhortations of the Fryars whom he ſent abroad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Commons to perſwade them of the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the act in regard of it ſelfe, the omiſſion thereof expoſing them to unavoydable miſeries by forraigne enemies, and the acceptable ſervice which thereby they might doe the Catholike King, and the glorious office they might doe their Countrey, prevailed ſo far, that they willingly ſeemed to bring in what he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded rationally.</p>
               <p>The Gallies of <hi>Algier</hi> and <hi>Tunis</hi> were abroad at the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ceriale</hi> pilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Pyrates of <hi>Algier.</hi>
                  </note> ſame time, had burnt and pillaged in the State of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa</hi> the towne of <hi>Ceriale,</hi> neare to <hi>Final;</hi> thence carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away 400 priſoners, and proceeding further, had ſacked the Sea-coaſt of <hi>Sardinia,</hi> plundred the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, taken away the veſſels of Plate and Ornaments,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:178347:56"/> and returning home, were met withall by the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Berdeaux,</hi> who knowing that theſe Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Pyrats had not taken thoſe ſpoiles out of the lands of the Chriſtian, but his enemies dominions would not fight againſt them, but, inquiring of the prizes, and finding the Church utenſils in their hands, (religion and this pious obſervation of thoſe conſecrated veſſels, overcomming his hoſtile diſpoſition to the Catholike King) he redeemed thoſe Eccleſiaſticall goods with his money, and ſent them backe to <hi>Sardinia,</hi> to be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their proper ends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sicily</hi> was the next place which thoſe Pyrats threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and <hi>Melchior Borgia</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generall, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, ordered 15 <hi>Neupoliian</hi> Gallies, (which then lay at <hi>Legorne)</hi> to make to Sea preſently after them, but they returned without doing any thing, the Pyrats out-ſayling them. Sixe Gallies of <hi>Malta</hi> being about the beginning of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> arrived at home from <hi>Trapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> were counter manded by the great Maſter for <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> to joyne there with their <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſquadrons, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Byſertains,</hi> and the other Pyrats which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to diſpeople and ruinate the Sea-coaſts of that part of Chriſtendome. <hi>Nari</hi> the Prior was appointed for their General, who landing upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Turkiſh ſhore, to take in freſh water, was endangered by an Ambuſcado of <hi>Turkes,</hi> which lay there, and ſlew ſome of his men, and wounded him with a Muſquetado in the arme, yet he fortunately arrived at <hi>Naples, Auguſt</hi> the 6. new ſtile, and went to viſit the Viceroy then reſiding at <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> but the fleet was imployed other wayes; the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gallies ſhaken with ſtormes, and the tempeſts which they had endured in the gulph <hi>de la Speti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to tranſport <hi>Don Melchior Borgia</hi> into <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the <hi>Maltiſan</hi> Gallies were to convey the Regent of the Vicaria of <hi>Naples</hi> to <hi>Florence,</hi> whither he went in the quality of the extraordinary Embaſſadour to the Catholike King, to congratulate the great Duke for his late marriage with the Princeſſe of <hi>Rovera,</hi> of the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:178347:57"/> houſe of <hi>Vrbin,</hi> which was ſolemnized at <hi>Florence, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> the 5. new ſtile, in the preſence of Cardinall <hi>Cappo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> and the Dukes of <hi>Parma</hi> and <hi>Modena.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Kingdome of <hi>Naples</hi> in the <hi>interim,</hi> ſuffered <note place="margin">The Bandetti in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> executed.</note> much by the inteſtine commotions of its owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, <hi>Bandittes</hi> and other male-contents. <hi>Franciſco Caraffa,</hi> Prince of <hi>Lupino,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Salzi</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Straboni,</hi> the Signiors <hi>Ceſari</hi> and <hi>Aſcanio</hi> of <hi>Bolognia,</hi> and ſome other <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Lords, heads of the commonalty of <hi>Nid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Capna,</hi> had challenged the Cavilliers of other commonalties to ſingle duels, and for this fact were condemned by the Collaterall to have their heads ſtrucke off, yet becauſe they conſented willingly to the contributions which the Vice-Roy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, upon the interceſſion of the Regent <hi>Brancia,</hi> Duke of <hi>Belvidier,</hi> and the Nobleſſe of the Kingdome to the Vice-Roy, the ſentence was not abrogated, but altered, they were onely baniſhed to ſeverall places. But the ſentence and execution of the <hi>Banditti Luigi Taglialatela</hi> was exemplary and unchangeable: He was apprehended in his Fort with ſome of his companions, beheaded, and his ſcull was carried to <hi>Giuliano,</hi> the place where he was born, and there ſet upon an iron barre, in the place where his houſe once ſtood, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing raſed to the ground, and ſown with ſalt. Piety commands juſtice againſt ſuch malefactors, and policy will have it exemplary. The ambitious heads of ſuch ſtinking Poppies muſt be cut off, to pardon ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents lifes, is to give life to their inſolencies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here we are becalmed, &amp; though we ſee the ſheare of</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary <hi>ſomwhat more glorious, by the happy ſucceſſe of our little Engliſh Fleet which lay before</hi> Sally, <hi>ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not yet reach it. S.</hi> Hilary <hi>ſhall perfect that ſtory, which crowneth our Nation, and makes it deſervedly called</hi> Gentem Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricem. Dum ſua reſtituit ſpoliato jura patrono,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>With a perfect narration of other Occurrences both by Sea and Land, wherof we have already obtained ſome bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viates, &amp; do daily expect more, which we purpoſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue &amp; publiſh by the time promiſed, if God permit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:178347:57"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
